Make sure mine's muted.
>> Good afternoon and welcome to the April
20th, 2026 Public Service Committee.
Please turn off or silence your cell
phones and mute your devices if you're
online.
To make a com a public comment online,
please use the raised hand function. To
make a comment, a public comment in
person, please come up to the podium,
turn on the green light, and give us
your name. And um I we can do both
podiums.
Upon completion of our agenda items,
there'll be no further business
discussed.
Will the clerk please read the first
agenda item?
>> Number 13, ordinance third reading
amending section 13.20.050
general prohibitions and section and
section 13.20.070
local limits of chapter 13.20 20
wastewater treatment and disposal of the
code of the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming to
revise local discharge limits and
related provisions in compliance with
MPDES and WPDES
permit requirements.
>> Hey, do we have a staff report?
>> Yes, madam chair and council members.
Matt Bulo shine board public utilities
water recognition division manager. Uh
Minnesota should have supplied all of
you with the newest limits. they changes
a couple thousands just updating them
per EPA. With that, um I would like to
make a request to delay this motion. Um
reason being is because the EPA has not
started their 30-day um public approval
or comment section yet. So, what we're
fearful of is we're going to approve it
through council and then EPA is going to
have comments. We're have to come back
to you guys and do the three readings
again. So, I don't know exactly how many
I can request. If I can do two weeks, if
I can do a month delay.
Do we have questions for the staff?
>> Yep. And other than that, be happy to
answer any questions.
>> Oh, I'm sorry, Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, chairman Emmanu.
So, if we So, the initial set that we
were given had already been through the
30-day EPA review. They It had not
either. So, we were going to act on that
without it having been through that
process.
>> So, through your chairman. Um, yeah,
we're going to approve this. Usually
what EPA does is as soon as they hear
that we're we're going in front of
council to get the ball rolling, they
get the ball rolling on their end. They
haven't got the ball rolling on their
end. So they they've gotten the the same
thing that you guys have have gotten as
well as the the fine tuning of it with
the 3000s, you know, the difference of
the thousands of uh the parameter
checks, but they're they're rolling the
ball just as well as we are. We just
don't want you guys to approve it and
then have to come back to you guys three
months from now and get it approved all
over again.
>> Okay. Thank you.
Okay. Are there any other questions?
Okay. Um, thank you.
>> Yep. Thank you.
>> Is there public comment online or in
person on this item?
>> Okay. Go ahead, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Oh, okay. Um, regarding item 13. Oh,
sorry. For the record,
sorry. For the record, this is Charles
Miller.
Um,
sorry, one second here.
My dog just got got a little out of
control. Um
uh regarding item number 13, the
engineering evaluations attached to this
ordinance indicate a legal increase in
the maximum daily discharge limits for
highly toxic industrial pollutants,
including benzene and BTEX.
I'm requesting the committee state on
the public record exactly how much the
board of public utilities will have to
spend annually to filter the increased
concentration of these petroleum
hydrocarbons.
If this body is raising the ceiling on
industrial contamination,
the taxpayers have a right to know the
exact dollar amount of liability you are
shifting onto the public water
reclamation facilities before you vote.
Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Miller.
Is there anyone else? Jennifer.
Okay.
Uh then I'm going to close public
comment. Can I get a motion and a
second?
>> I would move to postpone.
>> Motion to confirm.
>> I'm sorry. I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> And I would move to postpone.
>> Okay. We have Dr. um Aldrich has moved
to approve and uh postpone.
Dr. Renie seconded to approve and um
Councilman Laburn uh motion to or
seconded to postpone.
Is there any discussion from the
committee?
>> Madam Chairwoman, I do have a question.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> according to our action report, we were
supposed to amend by substitute. Do we
want to
make that amendment before postponing.
>> Yes.
>> Matt,
>> are you German? Yes.
>> Okay. So, Madam Chairwoman, I would
recommend we vote no on postponement
until we make the requested amendment.
>> I have a question of clarification. Dr.
Aldridge. Um, if we are postpon I mean
we're postponing this to hopefully have
the EPA have time to review this.
Wouldn't it be more prudent to wait
until they've reviewed it to make that
substitution in case there needs to be
another set of substitutions
>> through you, Madam Chair? Um, from what
we understand, so it's approvable by
It's confusing. I I admit it is
confusing. So, what we sent them before
is what you guys had in the first place.
It is approvable by EPA and then we sent
it to the council and then usually they
run concurrently with us. This time they
did not. Um, so this is just going to be
a delay in what we've given you. um
it'll just the only time that they'll
come back and say no these these
limitations don't match is if they get
public comments from that from any kind
of industrial user or any kind of FSE or
anything like that
>> okay
>> Dr. there any
>> I'm not sure that answer the C answered
the council woman's question so our our
so the required um substitute gives new
figures or updated figures if I'm
correct
>> correct you mad
>> all right and those have those been
submitted to the ETA already
>> yes you madam chair those have been
submitted to EPA as well so you're
getting the same thing they're getting
it's just running it through the city
council and EPA at the same time you
guys are a little bit ahead of the ball
compared to
>> Thank you madam chair one
>> okay So, we have a motion to
>> to postpone and a second.
Um, any more discussion? All those in
favor?
>> Councilman Labour.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. Go ahead, Dr. Councilman
Leborn.
>> Uh, thank you, Madam Chairman. Um,
I guess before I I vote, I'd like to
understand I believe what I've just
heard is that uh the substitute would be
appropriate and that that would be the
information that we should send on to
the EPA. So, uh that postponement
in my opinion should come after we adopt
u the substitute if we choose to. And I
think that it's clear that this is a
little unusual, but uh so I I speak in
opposition to the uh
>> postponement
>> the postponement that I supported. Uh so
we can uh I guess we got to vote that
down first and so uh we can do that.
>> Okay.
All those in favor of the postponement,
please signify by saying I. Those
opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay. So, the amendment has failed.
>> I would move.
>> Go ahead.
>> The substitute uh and moved Yeah. to
amend by substitution the substitution
that was provided to us um that is dated
>> April 7th.
>> April 7th, whatever date.
>> Second.
>> Okay. So, Dr. um Aldridge has moved and
it's been seconded by Dr. Renie to uh
approve the substitution.
Is there any discussion?
Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, we're going to open that up
for public comment. Is there anyone who
would like to comment on the amendment
either online or in person?
Okay,
seeing none, any other discussion? Okay,
all those in favor of the amendment,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed?
Okay. I would move to postpone
>> two weeks.
>> Well, is two weeks going to be enough?
>> Yeah, but I think a month,
>> Madam Chair, to Dr. Eldridge, as long as
you guys can. They were thinking two
months is what we're thinking. So I
don't know if you can do two months.
>> I would move to postpone or so
Jennifer
>> point of point of order. Madam Chair,
historically we had one of our attorneys
rule several years ago that we can only
postpone from one meeting to the next.
So if we need a longer postponement, we
just have to chain them together.
>> U Mr. Brooks.
>> Yes. Council members Brad Brooks,
director of BOP. I apologize. This is so
I'm I'm
embarrassed just set and listening to
it. The issue is EPA will not start
their process until it goes before the
city council.
My preference to them would be, hey,
let's just wait till you get it all
approved, then we bring it to our city
council. The issue with that is is they
will not start their 30-day
advertisement until then. So if we do
that, it just pushes everything off. So
I think the best thing to do, we we can
postpone it, but it all we're telling
you is that maybe more than one or two.
If we can't do that, then we need to let
them know and we'll work through it. But
we appreciate your patience and
willingness to work with it. We thought
we were ahead of the game and they were
proceeding. Bottom line, they were not.
That's unfortunate for all of us, but
that's the main issue here. It's
it's just working with with EPA. So,
>> Dr. Alwoman Emmens through you. So, are
they going to start that 30-day review
period from the time we uh postpone this
or is it going to be from the time it's
actually gone through the approval
process? Because if we postpone now and
they don't start the review, we're not
helping you.
>> They started early.
>> When do they start?
>> Week, two weeks.
So
to you uh chair through Matt, they may
start one or two weeks.
So um
let's let's just table it. Okay, we'll
get with EPA, get back with you. Um but
we've got to work something out on our
end with them. But but that's the big
culprit is they will not start. So
>> we we'll we'll postpone for two weeks.
will come back before you hopefully have
some updated and we can get them
advertising it. So, um I think one of
the other things they don't realize the
implication this creates for us and the
confusion. So, it's just again we're
working with EPA. We got to work with
them. They're the governing body over
this. So, I apologize. It is confusing
but I just want to come up and stress
that from from me myself. So,
>> thank you.
>> Okay. So, Dr. Aldridge, you made
>> I would move to postpone two weeks.
>> Okay.
>> Second.
>> Uh so Dr. um Aldridge moved and
Councilman Leborn seconded.
Um so now we need to go back out for
public comment. Is there any comment on
this in person or online?
Jennifer,
>> Tim Gbach, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Okay, thank you. Um, I just want to uh
My name is Tim Gbach. I work for
and the owner of 403 Compliance LLC.
Um,
I was involved with the development of
local limits um for a company called LS
Pre-Treatment Consulting.
And
kind of the terminology I'm hearing that
um might not be accurate is
EPA review. EPA has reviewed and deemed
uh the local limits package as
approvable.
What what's happening here is
um
they typically will not start the 30-day
public notice period until it's gone
through at least one council reading.
So now we've gone through some council
readings.
uh the Smittle has been provided to the
EPA
for public notice and now we're kind of
at the mercy of the uh the EPA schedule
when they will public notice it. So
that's what's causing the delay is
um
the amount of time it will take them to
actually public notice to make these uh
limits legally defensible.
So, it's um they have they have reviewed
and they have deemed the limits
approvable
and now to make them legally defensible,
they're starting the 30-day public
notice period.
>> Oops. Thank you, Mr. Grossback.
Is there any other public comment? Mr.
Miller, you can unmute yourself.
Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Uh, for the record, Charles Miller, I'm
commenting on this amendment and the
ongoing confusion regarding the
discharge limits. This committee just
spent the last 15 minutes debating the
procedural sequence of the EPA's 30-day
review period. The BOPU director just
stepped to this microphone and stated he
is embarrassed by this process. But what
is truly embarrassing is that this
committee is using procedural confusion
to completely dodge the financial
reality of what you are amending.
Whether you pass this substitute
amendment today or postpone it for two
months to appease the EPA, the
engineering documents remain the same.
This amendment legally raises the
discharge limits for highly toxic
industrial pollutants, including benzene
and BTEX into our public water
reclamation system. I will ask the
question that you just ignored. What is
the exact dollar amount of liability and
increased filtration costs being shifted
onto the Laram County taxpayers and BOPU
by allowing corporations to dump higher
concentrations of these petroleum
hydrocarbons? Do not hide behind EPA
sequencing delays. If you are going to
amend and codify these limits, you owe
the public the financial math right now.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller.
>> Okay. Any other public comment?
>> Uh Tim Gbach, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Thank you. Can you hear me? Yes.
>> Okay. Um, in response to Mr. Miller's
uh, conversations regarding BEX and
benzene,
uh, this local limits evaluation does
not make any changes to the current
limitations in the municipal code for
benzene and BEX.
>> Thank you, Mr. Gbeck.
Any other comments?
Okay. So, I'm going to close public
comments. Um, discussion from the
committee.
Councilman Lebornne, please.
>> Uh, thank you, Madam Chairman. Um,
as has been pointed out here, that twoe
postponement issue uh comes from a uh
opinion from city attorney some years
ago. And I wonder if that's the opinion
of our current city attorney. It seems
to me that uh sometimes uh when we look
at that uh we ought to look back on the
original intent and I'm not seeing
necessarily in this case but it comes up
from time to time and sometimes uh a
longer postponement might be in order.
So, uh, I'd like to request the review
from the city attorney's office of that
original, uh, uh, opinion and see if
that still is the belief of the city
attorney's office because I think more
flexibility would be appropriate. But
nevertheless,
uh, I certainly speak in favor of this,
uh, postponement, uh, for obvious
reasons. And I'd point out that uh when
you look at some of these requests like
the one we just heard,
separating out cost of different
chemical elements out of our uh stream
of all the waste that goes into the
treatment plant is obviously totally
impossible. So um
asking me to document that is out of the
question. it just can't be done. That's
part of everything that goes in there
and the limits need to be established,
but a cost cannot be established.
So, um that's my response and I I would
point out that uh I recently toured the
treatment plant and it is uh really uh
fascinating to see all that goes into uh
treating that waste and coming out with
a clear product that goes back into Crow
Creek uh in in the proper manner. So all
of this discussion about uh
well I haven't heard a lot of discussion
here today but yes it costs it's
expensive but we have a great team at a
great facility that meets that important
effort of returning that water to that
creek
uh in a in in the proper manner because
it wasn't always that way. And uh
certainly it's quite complex but it is
uh a matter of fact. So I think a
postponement's in order and I appreciate
everything that uh the department does
at that treatment plant and I want to
note that establishing cost is out of
the question. Thank you.
>> Thank you m Thank you Councilman
Lebornne Dr. Renie.
>> Thank you Madam Chairman. I just want to
point out that effectively this is be a
recommendation on Monday night. Monday
night will be postponed for two weeks.
So it's really a three-week postponement
before it gets back to council. It'll be
a month before it comes back to this
committee.
>> Okay, we have a motion and a second on
the table. Any further discussion?
Okay. All those in favor of the
postponement, please signify by saying
I. I.
>> Those opposed. Okay. So the
recommendation
um for the or uh ordinance at the next
council meeting will be to approve
>> to postpone
>> postpone. I'm sorry to postpone after
all that.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Next ordinance third reading amending
section 2.76.040
040 designation of downtown development
district of chapter 2.76 downtown
development authority of title 2
administration and personnel of the
municipal code of the city of Cheyenne
Wyomi to expand the downtown development
district.
>> Okay. And staff report.
>> Good afternoon. Uh Sophia May, executive
director of the downtown development
authority for the record. There have
been no updates to this item since um
last council meeting.
Do we have any questions for uh Miss
Mazize?
Okay. Any public comment?
Okay. Uh can I get a motion?
>> I would move to approve on third and
final reading.
>> Second.
>> So we have a motion to approve and a
second.
Uh any discussion from the committee?
Okay. Hearing none. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
Okay. So, um the recommendation from the
public service committee will be to
adopt at the next governing board
meeting or governing governing body
meeting.
Next item.
>> Number 16. Ordinance second reading.
Amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
ID, east of Southwest Drive from County
Light, County LI Light Industrial, AG
Agricultural, and AR Agricultural
Residential to LI Light Industrial.
>> Staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair and members of the
committee, my name is Seth Lloyd. I'm
with the city of Cheyenne Planning and
Development Department. The proposal in
front of you proposes changing um the
land located southeast of I80 and
Southwest Drive from um various zones AR
ag uh agricultural rural agricultural AG
agriculture and LI light industrial to
LI light industrial. Um due to a unusual
aspect of the original annexation back
in the day, the property to the north of
this land is actually currently county
LI. We've been treating it as city LI
and should this zoning fail, we'll bring
a corrective ordinance with you. But as
long as we're looking at the other two
parcels, we'll loop that one in for this
at this time. Um the parcels uh are
surrounded by LI zoning on three sides.
Um and uh the PUD to the west is also an
industrial zone within that PUD. Um so
the proposal is compatible with majority
of the surrounding area. However, there
is some residential to the southwest of
this property. Um the property is
largely vacant or used for agricultural
type purposes. Um so zoning at LI would
give more uh options and opportunities
for development. Um the only uh issue I
guess with this proposed zone change is
the future land use map. Um the future
land use map shows the area as mixeduse
residential and that's anticipating a
mix of mostly residential and a little
bit of commercial uses. Also the area to
the north is mostly mixeduse commercial.
Um, based on this, the future land use
map for the area would anticipate this
entire southwest corridor to develop
with residential and commercial uses and
solely evolve away from light industrial
uses that are there. Now, um, knowing
that the applicant has also submitted a
future land use map amendment for this
area that those items are later on
today's agenda. Um, the basically if the
future land use map amendment passes,
uh, we would recommend approval of this
zone change. Uh, if the future land use
map amendment does not pass, staff would
recommend denying this zone change. Um,
I would note that this is a zone change,
so it has three readings. Um, and the
resol the future land use map amendment
is a resolution, so it will be
considered before the zone change is
considered. Um, I would ask that you go
ahead and support this application today
and then should the resolutions fail um
at the next committee meeting, we can
address that issue with this zone change
at that time. So staff's recommendation
is uh at least approve for today. Um and
depending on your uh uh decision on the
future land use map amendment, either
approve or deny when the time comes for
final consideration of this item. I'm
available for any questions.
>> Mr. Lloyd, those are items 27 and 28. Is
that correct?
>> Correct.
>> Okay. Questions for staff?
Yes, Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um, so first and foremost, I'm just
curious. I see where we had notified
neighbors um about this proposed change.
Have we had any neighbors who have
commented or reached out to your office?
>> Madam Chair, we had one neighbor reach
out prior to the planning commission
meeting um and they were against this
development. Um they had concerns, well,
let me rephrase that. They had concerns
about traffic and the LI zone would
likely increase traffic in the area. So,
we assume they'd be against uh the that
development of the parcel, but their big
concern was traffic in the area and
traffic on Southwest Drive. Um it is
notable that uh from this property, your
only real access um that is clear is to
go south on Southwest Drive. Um you can
go north, but occasionally that gets
blocked for long periods of time. Um so,
they had concerns about the traffic in
the area and how this would increase
traffic. Um, but we haven't had uh no
one showed up to the planning commission
meeting to discuss this item from the
public and we haven't had any comments
since that time either.
>> Followup question. Um, chairwoman Amens
for you. So, right now, my understanding
and knowing this area um from having
worked out in that area for quite a
while, this is actually a tree farm
right now and it sits across the street,
if you will, or the road from the
Cheyenne Animal Shelter. And um
is there a reason why Light Industrial
might be a better choice than for
instance? because I'm thinking that a
tree farm might be a great um
opportunity for an urban farming, but I
also see in their back in the background
that you've provided us that there may
be other planned uses for this property
that they haven't stated,
>> Madam Chair, uh through you. Um so the
property does have a tree farm on it
now. Um tree farm is a use that can be
done in the LI zone. Um so they could
continue to use it for that or they
could expand that. Um it's my
understanding from the applicant that
they have um options that they're
looking into for this land and quite
frankly the AR zone is one of our most
limiting zones and the AG has a little
bit more options but oftent times those
are via conditional use. Um and so the
LI zone would allow for more urban style
development in this area. Um but I'll
let the applicant address any any plans
for future use for this area. But
generally speaking, um staff would re
would uh anticipate that this area would
be um zoned to a more urban zone at some
point, whether that's mixeduse
residential to go with comprehensive
plan, residential or commercial or
industrial, some sort of um urban zone
to allow more urban development. Right
now, it's kind of a more agricultural
zoning area.
>> Thank you.
Other questions?
>> Go ahead, Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um, Seth,
what is the status of the uh corridor
study on Southwest Drive? Um, I remember
we began it a while back. I assume it's
done by now, but uh that's really a
narrow road and um I'm wondering the
more we add to it and that obviously the
the people live out there are concerned,
what possible improvements might be
coming for Southwest Drive? Isn't that a
recommendation of the corridor study?
>> Madam Chair, through you. The southwest
drive corridor study was um um
initiated by the metropolitan planning
organization. It went through the
metropolitan or planning organization's
processes and the metropolitan
organization will still use that as kind
of a guiding document. However, it did
not go through the city processes to be
approved as a city plan. So, the city
will at the moment the city does not use
that as a guiding document when
reviewing things like this. It's kind of
a weird nebulous area because the NO is
kind of anticipating that and and
leaving that as an option on the table,
but since the city didn't adopt that
plan, um the city might have to um work
out uh some of their own recommendations
with development in this area. My
recollection is that one of the
recommendations from that plan was
actually to make Broken Arrow a more of
a more of a major roadway, take some of
that traffic off the southwest drive.
Broken Arrow was more distant from the
intersection with um uh with College and
I25.
So, um that intersection spacing would
work would help work things out a little
bit better. Um however, as I said, it it
it's kind of in a little bit of a gray
area. It might still be an idea to move
forward in this area, but because it
wasn't adopted by the city, um it's not
really controlling at this time.
>> Followup.
>> Go ahead.
>> Well, thank you, Seth. Yeah, that's uh
brings up some interesting points here
because as as it grows and as uh and
this area has been uh this this
particular parcel has been part of a lot
of discussion going back many years, but
um I guess what you're suggesting is
that
or what I'm suggesting
is that we need to adopt that as a city.
This this is not out on the edge of town
anymore. It's it's in the city and and
we really need to adopt that plan. Uh
controversial is the uh is it broken
arrow that was such problem?
>> We need to resolve that. They're just
more growth, more use and it's a very
inadequate
roadway for that kind of urban use. So,
and I know it won't happen right away,
but we definitely ought to be making uh
uh use of that corridor study. I see Mr.
Bloom seems to have something to say.
Chair, it's for you, uh Charles Bloom,
planning the development director,
members of the committee. Um yes, we had
the corridor plan. It ran into some
snafoos that was adopted by the the
county commissioners, but not the city
governing body. Um what it did was it
evaluated two collector streets that are
shown on our current major street plan.
One being a major collector which is
Southwest Drive and the other one being
a minor collector which is Broken Arrow.
All it did was it essentially was a
feasibility study to say, "Hey, how can
we develop these roads and how can we
utilize public input to develop those
rights of way?" since it was not adopted
um by the city. The way we look at it as
they're both collector roads, they'll
both be built as a standard collector um
as they develop in the future. And if
there are alternatives such as different
ways to mitigate or move an intersection
over, then we would have to evaluate
those independently. So today, if it
were developed um in that area, either a
broken arrow or southwest, we'd make
sure that those have adequate rights of
way um when they are being developed. So
it wouldn't really change the the grid
or the location of those roadways.
>> Thank you.
>> Do you have a question,
Dr. Renie?
>> Yeah, thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Um
through you to Mr. Lloyd. So
the the surrounding areas as you've
described are already light industrial.
That's correct
>> Madam Chair that is that is correct. The
surrounding area on three sides is light
industrial.
>> Okay. And part of the problem if I read
this on your criteria
um for the eight says it does not comply
but that's because of the current
existing map that's there. And if we
change the
change the map to reflect the current
use then those things those criteria
would comply. Is that correct madam
chair? Yes. So I I've I've moved to the
future land use map on the screen here.
And you can see that it's not really
industrial anywhere east uh sorry west
of the BNSF railroad. Um all of that is
anticipated by the future land use map
to develop with a mix of commercial and
residential development. um that was the
plan back in circuit 2014 I want to say
is when this plan was adopted. So things
may have changed since that time but at
that time the anticipation was that we'd
get more residential development in this
area. However, the existing conditions
in the area is definitely largely light
industrial. So the question really
becomes when we talk about the future
land use map amendment later on today's
agenda. Is it appropriate to continue to
anticipate this area develop with
residential development or is it better
to recognize the light industrial that's
kind of already around there and
continue that as more of an industrial
corridor?
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Uh Chairwoman, uh just a quick question.
Why is there a cutout um on this
property uh that's not platted? It shows
on our map is not platted. What? Why are
we not Is that owned by a different
entity?
>> Okay,
>> Madam Chair, that is correct. It is
owned by a different entity.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay.
Thank you, Seth.
Okay. Any public comments either in
person or online?
Madam chair through you John Sers's
agent for true grid on this particular
project
as Seth pointed out with is obviously
the LI questionable the AG the AR it's
surrounded by LI we do have currently
have our tree farm out there for bison
brand at this time we plan on continuing
to have that on the front side we feel
that's a good location
in in an effort to combine all the
properties to one zoning we looked at
the LI the LI fits a variety of
different idea is that we're getting
phone calls all phone calls on on a
daily basis for different options out
there. We're trying to get it all locked
into one piece. So then we can move
forward with what different design
options we can move forward with at this
time period. Without that, we're just
stuck until we have a full plan and
everybody's calling trying to figure
out. We have no intentions of putting a
data center there. So let's
certain things with work camps and data
centers I want to clear up. So that is
not involved in this particular
situation. Uh the parcel that you talked
about is Jeannie Grogan with Miranda. We
visited with her on possibilities and
shoes in favor of that. So there is that
in regards to as Seth pointed out URLI
to the north you're to the east to the
west. We have that as well. We've looked
at that being a residential home builder
this is not the area conducive for us to
build homes down in this area
particularly. We feel it is a light
industrial with all the uses
particularly to the north with chor
advanced and everybody over there as
well as white cap. So we don't see that
as a as a need for residential in that
area especially down in the corner at
this time period whatsoever. Um I know
that staff has talked that the mub piece
to the south um does garner some
possibilities of future who knows what
that comes before uh planning commission
in May. We have nothing to do with that.
are here. This is a separate individual
project and I just making sure we're
clear and I'm happy to address any
questions.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Sers. Any other
public comment?
Okay. Hearing none, can I get a motion?
Oh. Oh, I'm sorry.
>> Go ahead.
>> My name is Heather Madrid. I didn't come
here to speak on this issue, but I just
am curious if all of these traffic
analyses and other things are operating
in isolation and not taking into
consideration the rapid influx of data
centers among other things that are
currently already happening on the south
side of um town. As someone pointed out,
it is a really narrow corridor and it's
in absolutely terrible shape. Um, and my
concern is that it seems like
development starts happening before
infrastructure is updated and usable.
And it seems I mean that area
intersection of college and the multiple
different streets, it's already very
questionable when it comes to safety.
And I would just hope that as we're
planning all of these resonings and
annexations and whatever that studies
aren't being done in isolation because
there is unprecedented growth happening
particularly on the south side of town
right now and I would just ask that that
be all taken into consideration.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody else?
Can you turn on your microphone, please?
>> David Nicely, 200 Walters. Um, yeah, as
a resident of Walters Boulevard, looking
at the what appears to be rapid
expansion of residences and traffic, I
agree with Mr. Leborn that uh um
the city should be considering traffic
um in addition to the uses of the land.
We have a planning department to plan
for these things. Um, in my 20 years on
Walters Boulevard, I never imagined that
Walters would back up all the way to
Allison Road ever. And now we're getting
highdensity residential development to
the south of us. Um, and the board of
public the Metropolitan Planning
Organization told us in years ago that
they were going to expand Waltersh to
five lanes. There's no funding to do it.
There's no plan to execute that plan. Um
I keep calling and asking when are you
going to do it? When are you going to do
it? When are you going to do it? Nobody
can tell me. Um so I encourage the city
to plan for growth, especially if we're
going to take actions to proactively
prompt growth. Um let's not get the cart
before the horse. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Nicely. Anybody else?
Okay.
Can I get a motion and a second?
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay. Dr. Aldridge moved and uh Dr.
Renie seconded.
Um discussion from the committee.
>> Yes.
>> Go ahead, Dr. Aldrich.
>> Uh Chairwoman Amens. I I'm going to be a
yes vote on this today because I I
believe that a light industrial is not
going to change the use of what that
property is currently being used for. I
think it probably also is a better fit
for what's going on um in that little
business park that's to the north of um
Interstate 80 and to the west of
Southwest Drive. Um right now it allows
the company that's doing their business
there to continue to do that, which
would be a similar amount of traffic.
Um, but if this were to be reszoned, it
would need to come back before the
council again. Um, or if it were to be
platted and um, for anything that would
be used other than this um, light
industrial. So, um, for that reason, I'm
going to be a yes vote today um, in
order to um, give them the most
flexibility possible, understanding that
by doing this zoning change, we're not
anticipating any changes um, in traffic
at this point in time.
>> Mr. Liberal
Thank you, Madam Chair. Um, I just point
out that all of this development and all
of the important work that we have to
do, for instance, improving Southwest
Drive is dependent on funding.
And we would love to be able to uh
implement uh those uh improvements and
uh better traffic uh passage along a lot
of these roads. And certainly the there
to the south is experiencing a lot of
growth, but uh we can only do what we
can afford and what we can fund. and the
expectation that we can uh uh get ahead
of some of these things. Um when we do
have a functional roadway there is uh
just like any business or family or a
person uh we've got a plan and then
we've got to fund and then we've got to
build. and it doesn't uh you can't jump
over the fact that the economic uh
atmosphere that the city operates in is
uh got to fit the whole city. So I was
just trying to call some attention to
the fact that we need to pay more
attention to that area and get it uh
clearly uh more closer to uh that
improvement. But that improvement is
going to be expensive and so are the
other ones. So, uh, we can only improve
what we can afford and I think that
that's just all that is realistic. Thank
you,
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. I don't see
anybody from the no here, but since the
the Metropolitan Planning Organization
was brought up, they are the ones that
generally do long-term traffic studies
and they do try and coordinate things.
But perhaps it'd be not good if um we at
least could get a
report in our email from them on how
they do this and if it'd even be better
if somebody could show up um Monday
night to maybe briefly address some of
the just to give a brief explanation in
case anybody the public would like to
hear that. So thank you.
>> Okay, we have a motion and a second on
the floor. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I. I.
>> And those opposed.
Okay. So the recommendation from the
public service committee will be to
approve at the next meeting of the
governing body. Next item
>> number 17 ordinance second reading
pursuant to section 2.2.2 plan
development regulating plan or or
development master plan and section
5.6.2 to PUD planned unit development
district of the unified development code
amending ordinance number 4524 by
modifying certain standards of the
adopted district planned unit
development PUD for Sweetgrass located
southeast of the intersection of College
Drive and Avenue C.
>> Do we have a staff report?
>> Chair um Connor W with the planning and
development department. I know I'm
mixing it up a little bit. Jennifer gave
me a seat here up front because I've got
quite a few items that are probably
going to have some discussion coming up.
Um again, uh madam chair, members of the
committee, Connor White Planning and
Development Department, the item before
you is for a modification to the
Sweetgrass PUD. Uh so planned unit
development, just kind of some
background when it comes to the planned
unit developments, it's basically their
own special zone district for those
properties. They have their own
regulations, their own design standards,
various other things that are put into
them. Uh they don't follow the UDC uh
completely. Uh anything that's not
mentioned in the PUB does defer back to
the the city zoning code, but for the
most part, they are their own standalone
zone district.
With the Sweetgrass PUB, they have their
own um kind of internal zone districts.
Um they have their own kind of zoning
map kind of laid out for what is
planned. Uh, one of those things in
there is a community park. Uh, the
community park was part of the
annexation agreement. It is something
that is part of the PUD. It is located
uh towards the west side um south of
what is East Murray Road and kind of
butts up against Avenue C on the west.
Um,
with this amendment, what it does is it
reduces not reduces the park size, it
reduces the amount of park size that the
city would end up maintaining.
Um, so with the original PUD, basically
the roughly 67 to 70 acres was meant to
be dedicated to the city for the city to
maintain and develop. The POD amendment
reduces that down to 45 acres uh that
the city would basically develop and
maintain and allows for the other
portion to be developed privately with
recreational uses. So like a private
recreational facility um or something
along those lines where basically it's
not the city maintaining it or
developing it be privately developed but
still recreational uses.
So that is really the biggest part of
this. Um
the other section that is added in, it
does allow for them to have some
flexibility for amendments uh when it
comes to land uses within the PUD. Uh so
they did add a section that's similar to
our zone change requirement that they
would go through if they're changing
kind of minor internal zonings that
would still have to go through a public
process, but they'd be all kind of
internal.
But yeah, the the biggest portion of
this amendment is just changing some of
the park requirements. Does not reduce
again does not reduce the park size,
does not change the location, does not
remove it uh from the PUD. It's just
reducing how much the city will be
required to basically develop and
maintain and then allows the public
development of the other portion.
Planning commission did hear this. They
did recommend approval and I am
available for any questions.
>> Thank you, Dr. Renie. Thank you, Madam
Chairwoman. Um to through you to Mr.
White.
So
we're going to have 60 65 acre park
there. The city's going to maintain 45
acres of it. 15 to 20 acres are going to
be maintained by Sweetgrass. How how do
you envision this? I mean, are there
going to be two levels of are there is
there going to be a certain standard
that it's going to have to be developed
to as a park or are their amenities and
their level of maintenance going to be
different or is ours going to be
different from theirs? I mean, how do
you guys envision this working?
>> Madam Chair, through you. So, it depends
how So, I mean, the city park portion
will be maintained at our city park
levels. Um, so how we maintain Lion's
Park and all of that, that's the
maintenance for us
with how it privately develops that is
going to be it depends who is privately
developing. Is it going to be main
basically if SweetGrass doesn't have
somebody coming in to privately develop
it with um
like a private recreational facility
because that would end up being under
their ownership then rather than
SweetGrass most likely. or if they don't
and then SweetGrass develops it, then
it's maintained through their HOA.
I can let the developer or not
developer, but the agent for the
applicant speak probably more on that.
Um, but it it's they're going to be two
separate parcels. It would be divided
out. So, the city basically has our
parcel that would be dedicated to the
city and then you'd have the private
parcel. Um,
even with the private development,
they're going to have to meet all PUB
standards. they have to still meet all
HOA standards, whatever those are out
there. Um,
in short, there's probably going to be a
difference in maintenance because one is
city-owned and maintained. So, we will
maintain it to our standards and then
you've got depending on how the other
portion develops, either it's privately
owned and maintained or Sweetgrass owns
and maintains it to their standards.
Madam Chair, if I may.
So,
will the privately owned portion be open
to the public?
Madam Chair, through you.
That I don't know if I can answer. I
don't know the development plan for it.
If it is privately developed, uh, that
might be a question for the agent.
>> Okay. Madam Chair,
is again to Mr. white is um
I guess the question then is um
if it's
if it's not open to the public then
we're really just is the rationale did
the request come from Sweetgrass to do
this or did the city initiate the
request madam chair through you so the
request came from Sweetgrass our parks
department and our green. Our parks and
greenway planner did review the
amendment. They completely agree with
what is proposed. Um I believe our parks
department feels that 45 acres is more
manageable
um than the full 67 or 65 to 70 acres.
Um
they don't want to add any additional
parks on top of this for the city to
maintain. Um but they feel that the 45
acres is
um a better number than what was
originally proposed
but otherwise this this was spurred by
Sweetgrass themselves.
>> All right. Thank you, Madam Chairman.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Uh thank you Dr. Emmens. Uh through you.
So, Connor,
um I know you and I have had
correspondence about this development
because believe it or not, this is part
of W three.
>> And I have had many residents out there
contact me because um a lot of the
things that they were told when they
purchased homes out there have not come
to fruition. And good intentions are a
lot of times like crying babies in
church, their best when carried out,
right? And unfortunately,
that's not necessarily what's happened
out there. So, I'm really hesitant to um
decrease the amount of land that was set
aside for this public park. Um even if
it means that we're going to have less
to maintain, but I also um just
wondering about more concerning to me is
the land use amendments, the zoning
changes. Um that you said that this
would basically make it almost an
internal situation.
um there where if they were wanting to
change some of their zoning um that they
can do that uh if they're not doing it
in more than 25% according to this
document you gave us of the PUB parcel
um if they're doing it in less than 25%
um amounts that they basically don't
have to there's no oversight from the
council that it would basically be an
internal change. So, Madame Chair,
through you for clarification, it would
go through a it would still go through
the public process even for the 25%. It
just comes before you as a zone change.
So, like a zoning map amendment that we
would typically see rather than a
full-blown PUD amendment. Um, and they
would follow the uh basically our zone
change criteria and requirements. And
it's for it'd be for minor things such
as this portion um of their PUD is shown
as medium density residential and they
want to change that to a higher density
residential or vice versa. It'd be for
things like that where it's a small
change that they're making. If it was to
be especially for like the park acreage,
if they wanted to come back and they
wanted to basically change that whole
park acorage to something completely
different, make it all completely
commercial or something, that would be a
full-blown PUD amendment kind of what
we're going through where there's a lot
more notice requirements, a lot more um
kind of steps they have to go through.
The zoning map amendment portion that
they're adding is meant to be for those
minor. this subdivision that was planned
to be high density is maybe going medium
density or this medium density planned
subdivision they were going to do is now
going to go high density where they can
do that through the zone change process
uh rather than the the full-blown PUD
amendment.
>> A follow-up question Dr.
Um,
so
if they're if they don't
sell this or rent this or lease it to an
entity, then it would basically be the
homeowners association that would be
taking on the maintenance of this other
15 acres or whatever group they have out
there that's organized to do that. Madam
chair through you that is my
understanding from the applicant is if
this does not get sold to a private
entity to develop most likely Sweetcraft
Sweetgrass would then develop it and
maintain it as a park.
>> Would it followup questions
could it be because it also talks about
trails in here as well. Could it also is
it possible that there would be the 45
acre city park and then there would be
community trails and things that would
be counted as recreational
um acreage but not necessarily
um adjacent to the city property.
>> Madam Chair, through you um if I
understand the question correctly. So
the 45 acres is just for the city
portion of the park. We do have greenway
out here as well. And then Sweetgrass
itself has its own internal kind of
network of trails that they do with each
of their subdivisions that they
maintain. So there there is actually a
lot of open space I guess you could say
out in Sweetgrass. Um just the only
portions that the city is maintaining is
what we have dedicated as greenway like
actual greenway. And then it would be
this 45 acres.
So the through you chairwoman the other
15 acres roughly 15 to 20 acres could ne
it could be possibly trails it doesn't
necessarily indicate that it would all
be in one location in the subdivision.
Uh madam chair through you. So that
other 15 acres would be same location
because they have an actual park parcel
that is dedicated
>> basically not not fully dedicated yet
but is laid out in their PUD in their
plan um on various maps even has on the
future land use map it is shown as open
space and recreation basically. So they
have a specific area for that uh park.
So that's where the park and the the 15
acres and the 45 would be.
>> And follow up just as a reminder um
because it's been a couple of years
since you and I had this correspondence.
What how many uh PUD changes have we now
had to this particular thing? If I
remember correctly, it's around 18 mark.
>> Uh Madam Chair through you. This version
basically with should this version uh or
this amendment be approved? I believe we
are on amendment
five.
>> Okay. So, okay.
>> Or five or six. We're around
>> complete PUB
>> for the complete. Yeah. For the PUD.
They have done some minor PUD amendments
uh that they have laid out as something
they can do where just it's minor
technical things that we do
administrative. There have been two
major changes, I believe, that have come
before council, and they've had a couple
minor ones for various tweaks to the
code that weren't found by staff to be
major overhauls where they're changing
major components.
>> Thank you.
>> Hey, any other questions for staff?
Councilman Labour.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um,
since we have other major park
developments
uh underway at Tijuana's
and Rotary Parks. Um when is there some
timeline we could look at in terms of
when any development of this park is
going to begin? I believe that's just uh
completely empty now. Correct.
>> Madam Chair, through you. Yes. Currently
the land's not even dedicated to the
city at this point. Um it hasn't been
fully platted, hasn't been dedicated.
So, it is just vacant land.
>> I don't know if I have a timeline I can
give you. That's probably a better
question for our parks department. Maybe
even our parks and greenway planner is
if there's a timeline, but I believe
from just talking with our parks and
greenway planner a little bit.
This one's years out at this point
because again it comes down to funding.
It comes down to how are we going to be
able to develop the park without the
funding. And we do have Guanas Park that
I believe we are looking for that
funding to get somewhat developed there.
And then now we've got Rotary up on Dell
Range. So I don't know if I have a plan
for the park area. Again, a lot of it
comes down to funding. Um and where can
we find the funds to develop that?
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Um let's move on to public
comment.
Is there any public comment either
online or in person?
>> Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Um, uh, hi, Charles Miller. Regarding
item number 17, the sweet sweetg grass
PUD amendment. The testimony from staff
today is a stunning admission of
administrative retreat. You are moving
to slash the city's maintained park
commitment from 70 acres down to 45
acres because the parks department
claims the original mandate is
unmanageable. If the city cannot manage
the public assets it requires for
approval, it should not be granting the
density increases that necessitate them.
Furthermore, this amendment codifies a
25% loophole allowing the developer to
bypass the rigorous PUB amendment
process in favor of standard zone
changes for internal shifts. This is a
direct reduction in public oversight.
You are handing over promised community
land to an HOA while admitting on the
record that you cannot guarantee public
access to those 25 acres. I urge the
committee to hold the developer to the
original 70 acre public mandate and
reject the this private privatization of
promised community assets. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Any other
comments either online or in person?
>> No. Okay, I'm going to close the public
comment. Um, can I get a motion and a
second?
>> So, move.
>> Okay. Dr. I'm Dr. Mr. Dr. Leborn moved
>> a second
>> and Dr. Renie seconded.
>> Do we have discussion from the
committee?
>> No.
>> Okay. All those in
No.
>> Oh, I'm
>> okay. Okay. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> Opposed. No.
>> No.
>> Okay. So that a uh fails the recommend
there will be no recommendation from the
public service committee on that item at
the next governing board meeting. Next
item
>> number 18 ordinance second reading
annexing to the city of Cheyenne Wyoming
land west of Round Top Road and adjacent
to HappyJack Road.
>> Okay. staff report.
>> And madam chair, if you just give me one
second, I'll get my screen shared.
Madame chair, members of the committee,
Conor White, Planning and Development
Department.
So, the annexation before you, um, this
is for roughly 1,259.91
acres of land that is west of town,
along Happy Jack Road.
Uh, we did have the public hearing last
Monday. Uh, had lots of comments, lots
lots of questions. Um, I am going to go
through the criteria. Um, I do have a
bunch of bullet points. I believe those
were sent out as well to uh council
members and committee members. Um
the biggest ones that uh there were
questions on was probably criteria 1,
two, and three. Uh so those ones I'll
probably focus on more than the others.
So with criteria one, an annexation of
the areas for the protection of health,
safety, and welfare of persons residing
in the area and in the city or town.
This annexation improves the health,
safety, and welfare by uh bringing in
1,259.91
acres um under city building, fire, and
life safety codes, which provide uh more
consistent protection than
unincorporated standards. Fire station
one would be the responding station.
It allows for coordination of police and
fire response and a larger response,
improving emergency service coverage for
future development in the area.
I should note um
recent or not recently but within the
past two years we did annex North Range
Business Park uh that was annexed south
and that's south of HappyJack in this
area. So we do have fire and police
response out in this area already with
that annexation.
Access to city water and sewer instead
of relying on private wells and septic
systems reduces long-term groundwater
impacts uh that could also affect
downgradient properties.
City zoning allows the city to regulate
land uses, intensity, noise, and light
pollution, helping protect surrounding
rural resident residential areas and
ensuring uh more compatible development
patterns over time.
Number two is the urban development of
the area sought to be annexed would
constitute a natural uh geographical,
economical, and social part of the
annexing city or town. majority of the
area um is within the urban service
boundary on the long range comprehensive
plan. So plan Cheyenne
uh areas within the urban service
boundary are anticipated to be annexed.
So when plan Cheyenne was adopted,
anything within the urban service
boundary is anticipated to be annexed at
some point.
The area is a uh peninsula directly
connected to the city via a state
highway corridor which provides a
functional and geographical link. The
highway corridor supports local
development patterns and efficient
expand um extension of infrastructure
and services
with city zoning and utilities. Future
development will occur in a coordinated
manner uh with water and sewer services
instead of
uh dispersing wells and septic systems.
City zoning also enables regulations
again of noise and light improving
compatibility with the future
development in the surrounding area.
Over time, the area will naturally
orient towards Cheyenne for services,
employment, and commerce and will be
part of the social and economic fabric.
With criteria three, uh the area sought
to be annexed is a logical and feasible
addition to the annexing city or town
and the extension is based or and the
extension of basic and other services uh
customarily available to residents of
the city and town uh with reason be
available to the area proposed to be
annexed.
So the annexation is a logical extension
of the city due to direct adjacency and
access via the state highway corridor.
Police and fire services can be extended
immediately upon annexation ensuring uh
continue basically continuing of uh
public safety coverage. Again, fire
station one would be the response
station.
Water and sewer services can be feasibly
extended based on proximity to existing
infrastructure. So we do have water and
sewer in the area already.
Annexation allows the city to regulate
noise and light impacts.
Providing sewer and water services
avoids uh reliance on wells and septic
systems that can create environmental
and maintenance concerns.
And the area proposed for annexation is
adjacent to Northrange Business Park. on
December 9th, 2024, Northr Range
Business Park was annexed to the city
via ordinance 4593.
There are um more criteria. So number
four just talks about how um how
basically continu contiguous it is to
the city limits. Um with the annexation
due to the size of the property, it is
sitting at 5.26%
contiguous, but again that's based on
the size. If you change the annexation,
basically you annex a smaller area, that
number is going to increase and then you
can annex on top of that. So really the
contiguity is due to how large of a
parcel this is. Um number five is about
franchise utilities and those being in
place. The city has franchise utility
agreements with Black Hills uh that
provides electricity and natural gas.
And then number six has to do with um
basically the mailed notice which as I
stated on Monday, we did mail notice to
all property owners within 300 ft um
within the 20 days uh basically before
the annexation public hearing as well as
to utilities and the owners that of the
land.
There was some comments that came up
about this creating a pocket. Um,
this does not create a pocket.
The way that staff has looked at
pockets, um,
basically those areas have to be 100%
surrounded. I am going to pull up a map
that shows city limits.
I have the once this is up. I have the
parcel highlighted. The red area on the
map is city limits.
By annexing this land, it does not
create a pocket in this area. Um to get
100% basically surrounding the
neighborhood that is to
uh the east, it would take many more
parcels that would have to be annexed to
create an actual pocket.
So even going north, everything north up
to Horse Creek and even past Horse Creek
is all within the county.
So I know that was a comment that came
up and questions that came up about this
annexation creating a pocket, but from
staff's point of view and what we've
done with other county pocket
annexations, this would not create a
pocket. any county pocket annexation
that the city has initiated was when it
was a property or a group of properties
that are 100% surrounded by city limits.
Also, um again, another note I'll make
is that this is landowner petitioned.
This is not a city petitioned or city
initiated annexation,
I guess, except for city land that we
have um kind of added to the annexation.
The original petition is from the land
owner of the roughly 1,197
acres due to the board of public
utilities water treatment plant that's
out here being basically adjac adjacent
or contiguous to what is proposed to be
annexed. Um and the fact that
um the area was already being surveyed.
We did go ahead and ask if we could also
annex um the water treatment plant along
with this annexation.
Uh my understanding is Board of Public
Utilities has wanted to annex this land.
As the city owns the land, we can annex
our own land um and go through the
process that way as well. But it was
just easier to kind of tag on to the
petitioned annexation. But again, this
is landowner petition, not city
initiated.
Staff does recommend approval of the
annexation and I am available for any
questions.
>> Okay, questions for staff.
>> Okay.
So, um we'll Okay. Do we have a
representative?
Mr. Emmens.
>> Uh Madame Chairwoman, uh Dr.
and city council. Uh Brad Emmens, AVI
agent for the uh applicant, which is
William S. Revocable Trust. William S.
Cox Revocable Trust. Um this is just
wanted to confirm what Connor had said.
This is an initiation by the owner and
the developer for this uh parcel of
land. Uh the development would like to
uh use city water and sewer and
therefore that's the the the reason for
the annexation.
um it is contiguous with the city limits
and you know we believe that the best
way to uh develop this would be within
the city uh property. So we do have the
uh developer here as well today Tom
Glymire. So I'd like to turn it over to
him uh next and then uh he has some
other things to bring forward on the
project.
>> Good afternoon. My name is Tom
Galissmeer. I'm with Vio West Group.
Thank you council members for the
opportunity to speak today. Uh and thank
you all for showing up. Um I'd like to
first introduce myself uh and then our
company and briefly talk about our
project
and then introduce uh my partner as
well. Um as I said, my name is Tom
Galissmeer. I live in Colorado Springs
where I grew up. I've got a young family
down there. Um, we are
uh sad to see the PRCA leave, but
congratulations on that. I married a
cowgirl 11 years ago um who's a mounted
shooter, so I uh uh we're we're
disappointed that that's leaving our
neck of the woods, but congratulations.
Um I work for a group called Via West.
Uh we're a small group. We have about 45
people. It is headquartered in Arizona.
Um, I would like to share uh with
gratitude to my team. On Thursday night,
we were awarded owner developer of the
year by one of the largest real estate
organizations in Arizona. That is our
sixth such award over the last 10 years.
And I share that um as um I think a a
good representation of the thoughtful
and responsible approach that we have
taken over a long period of time. Um we
are contemplating a data center project
on this property. Uh we
believe that the industrial services and
natural extension of North Range uh are
attractive and there's plenty of land
out there. we will very thoughtfully and
responsibly build it out over the next
handful of years. It's not going to
happen all at once.
Um
it's going to bring a lot of long-term
jobs. Um we're owners and operators of
these long term. Uh we generally are
focused in the western states, Arizona,
Utah, Nevada, um and hopefully here. Uh
we f find that that's uh those places
are generally good uh
good and compatible with with with our
culture and our values.
Um I I'd like to also acknowledge uh the
memorial structure that is on the east
property line. Um it's about 200 feet
onto the property line and we just
learned last Monday night that there are
family uh with interest in it and we
100% support however they would like to
handle it and respectfully leave that to
the current property owner and the
family to discuss how to move forward.
Um I'd like to introduce um Jack O'Neal
um our our partner at Skybox.
>> Good afternoon. Um, first off, thank you
all everyone for the time and thanks
everyone for coming out and uh
appreciate all the effort that city
staff has put into this as well. Um, so
my name is Jack O'Neal. I'm from Dallas,
Texas, born and raised and uh I work for
Skybox Data Centers who's a 12-year-old
uh developer for data centers. Has only
done data centers for 12 years and we've
done it all across the country um
predominantly in uh Texas, uh Northern
Virginia, Chicago, um Santa Clara and a
few other small projects as well. Um I
am, uh was an engineer for about 5 years
for another data center developer. Um
I'm a mechanical engineer and math major
by education and kind of fell into the
data center industry on accident coming
out of school. Um and now I've been on
the developer side for a little over two
years now. Um, and the reason why I
chose to work at Skybox is because it's
a fantastic company owned by three
partners who are exemplary in what it
means to have a long-term partnership
with the city, the local constituents,
our customers, our capital partners. Um,
but most importantly, what does a
responsible development look like? Um,
we build data centers and I know y'all
are no uh stranger to some of them, you
know, with the large one, Northrange
Business Park and some of them coming
into uh South Cheyenne as well. Um, but
I mean we're using one right now for
this Zoom where uh all the photos and
videos on your iCloud of your family are
all stored in data center and those are
just some of the examples that you'll
use it for for medical records and
Spotify or any of your favorite
streaming services. Um this exploding
growth of our industry has uh caused us
to look at new opportunities and we felt
that this would be a fantastic
opportunity because it's separated from
any residential by at the furthest
northeast corner on the eastern boundary
by at minimum of a little over 1500 ft
um from some ranchets. There's a large
burm in between the two properties that
should protect some line of sight. Um
and then it has ready access to
HappyJack Road for ingress and egress
for uh any city services like fire or
police as well. Um we're pursuing the
annexation because we want to partner
with the city. Um these things kick off
a tremendous amount of tax basis which I
know uh uh the leads group will go into
a little bit more than detail. Um but
that's the just the project level of
what we'd like to engage with. We also
like to engage with the city um and our
projects in Hut and Lancaster. We
partnered with the Hutau Police
Department to help stand up a program
that they were really looking to do,
which was their drone program. Um, we'd
like to come and ask, you know, what
does Fire Station One need? Um, how can
we contribute? How can we be a player to
just the city and the county? Um, and
just we want to be good patrons and hire
as many local professionals as possible.
We anticipate this project to be about
350 to 500 full-time high-paying jobs
when it's fully built out. Um and it'll
be an uh investment that'll be quite
significant to the tax base um and kind
of pile on to what the active data
centers do. They have very minimal um
traffic once fully completed. There will
be some traffic during construction
absolutely um as does any construction
project have. Um but upon full
completion you know it's about you know
60 trips in and out each day um or for
each shift and then you're shifting you
know every eight hours. So it's pretty
minimal. Um, our water use, just want to
hit that one on the head. We are a fully
closed loop water system, which for
anyone who's not familiar with that,
that uses about as much as a res large
residential swimming pool. It's about 20
to 25,000 gallons to fill up one time.
And then it's sealed up and does not
emit any water. There's no evaporation.
There's no chemicals put into it that
would, you know, be discharged into the
local sewer system. Um, and we don't
touch groundwater at all. We're not
pulling out of the groundwater. We're
not discharging into groundwater. not
building wells, no septic. That is not
our goal or anticipation here. And um
that is exactly why we are pursuing city
services and paying our way for those
city services. Um from electricity as
well, we're working with Black Hills
Energy um handinand to make sure that we
are paying for 100% of our costs
responsible and no cost is passed on to
any of the local rateayers. Um being
from Texas, we have a large boom and
scheduled to be the largest data center
owner in a state perspective uh I
believe by 2030. And that is a question
that I would always ask is well how's
this going to affect my rate as well?
And uh we recently instituted some uh
legislation uh kind of following
actually what um other utilities have
already instituted to make sure that
that's not passed on to local rateayers.
So I was pretty proud of that and we are
uh played a big role into that. Um but
that is kind of it at a high level. Um
we love to be a great partner here. I'm
happy to answer any questions. And uh
we're also looking to set up hopefully a
local town hall here soon in the next
one to two weeks to kind of field
questions. Also, we've got a lot of
outreach for local businesses that want
to partner or supply equipment um as
well as labor. So, we'd love to have a
town hall to both field concerns and
also look how do we uh how do we partner
together. But thank you all for your
time.
>> Thank you. Do we have questions for the
developers? I do. Dr. Aldridge. Uh,
Chairwoman Evansu, I'm wondering if the
if this uh request to annex is um not
granted, uh will you will this project
go forward regardless um just as a
county project rather than a city
project?
>> It would be something we would very much
consider. Um but we would definitely
need to reync as a team because this is
our utmost priority.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other questions?
Thank you.
>> Thank you very much.
Okay, let's open it up to public
comment.
Go ahead, Betsy.
>> Good afternoon, Madam Chair, council
members. Uh Betsy Hail, I'm the CEO of
Cheyenne Leads. Um just for edification
of those online in the room, Cheyenne
Leads is a 40-year-old economic
development nonprofit. So, I do not work
for the city or the county. I work for a
private sector nonprofit. wanted to
address some uh questions that came up
in last week's hearing and predominantly
uh about the business parks and so I
believe you have a document and we left
some outside um you know we have a
40-year history of running business
parks our first business park was in the
Cheyenne business parkway business park
our first resident of that park was
Sierra Trading Post um our second
business park we started in the early
2000s the first resident of that park
was the Walmart distribution center
followed by the supercomputer for the
National Center for Atmospheric Research
um and then also Microsoft and also
Tri-State and UMC manufacturing. Wanted
to talk a little bit about the
importance of the business parks because
uh as Connor has said uh there is a
benefit to being on city water and sewer
and predominantly um we hear about the
concerns about water with the data
centers and so we have 12 operating data
halls in Cheyenne right now. They're all
in business parks. So um one of the
reasons for that is so that we can
ensure that they're not punching wells
and not being in septics so that we can
preserve our aquafers and groundwater.
Um the only data center that is proposed
and is under construction is the tall
grass uh cruso project which is in a
county pud. And as you heard from Connor
uh the county pud was how we built
Northrange Business Park and then that
was annexed in the end of 2024. Um, so
as we look at these 12 data halls, uh,
according to Frank from the Board of
Public Utilities, so I wanted to see
what was going on. I went to the Board
of Public Utilities annual report, which
is included with their audit. And if you
go to that uh site on the on the BOPU
site, you can actually see the report
that shows how much water the data
centers are using uh in gallons and then
what it's cost them. Uh and so you can
see who that compares with whether it's
the school district, the base, whether
it's uh the refinery, whether it's golf
courses, country clubs, those kind of
things. And so I would encourage folks,
but only 1.2% of the water that was
delivered to the customers in 2024 was
delivered to data centers. In 2025, that
number was actually uh 1.9%.
And as you can see, uh Frank goes on to
say that there won't be any rate
increases for future demand on the data
centers. The things I want to clarify uh
just as these two gentlemen mentioned um
Cheyenne Leads has managed almost hund00
million of infrastructure projects for
Microsoft and Meta. We ensure that they
pay for the water, the sewer, and that
they also pay for uh all of the utility
upgrades and the roads. And so just a
few things to think about. These are
available as well. If you have any
additional questions about uh how the
business parks work with the COAs and
things, just let us know. Thank you.
>> K McAdams. Um through the chair, I'd
like to address the council to consider
the impact of future data centers.
We've heard a lot about how much they
don't use. Well, let me address the
future issue of 40 data centers. Water
is another issue. The public is being
told data centers will lose will use
closed loop cooling systems. But that
does not mean zero water use.
Even low water systems still use
millions of gallons per year per
facility. Multiply that across multiple
data centers and it becomes tens or even
hundreds of millions of gallons over
time in a region that receives 15 inches
of precipitation a year. Many of these
systems also include backup cooling that
uses water during extreme heat, meaning
demand increases at exactly the same
the the same time under the system under
stress. The question is not whether they
use less water, but what guarantees
ensure water use remains low in practice
and over time. Residents must restrict
water use through drought. Can it be
guaranteed data centers must also
restrict their use?
Next,
power shows the same imbalance. A
typical Cheyenne resident pays about
around 13 to 16 cents per kilowatt hour,
while larger users can pay closer to 9
cents per kilowatt hour or less. Data
centers qualify at around 13 megawws
continuous demand, roughly the
equivalent of 17,000 homes. And that's
not the future buildout.
This is massive continuous usage
receiving discontinued discounted
pricing. They received discounted They
receive discounted pricing about 60
cents for every dollar residents pay.
These projects require major grid
upgrades. While companies pay some, much
of the cost can be spread across the
system. Meaning residents may end up
paying for infrastructure
built to serve private data centers.
If this is truly a good deal, it should
stand up to clear numbers and enforcable
protections because right now the risk
is public and the benefit is not. If you
are asking the residents of Cheyenne and
Larmy County to give up quality of life
to attract data centers to our
community, our community,
then we should receive the full value of
what is being given fair usage tax
revenue and the same rates for water and
electricity. It if it cannot be
guaranteed then these projects should
not be approved.
>> Thank you, M. Thank you. So I do want to
say to the group this issue is not about
data centers. This is about the the
annexation.
So please keep your comments to the
issue that that the um resolution or the
ordinance is about. It's about the
annexation.
Ma'am, did you want to go ahead? Oh,
Trisha.
>> Good afternoon, members of the
committee. My name is Patricia McCoy and
I'm here to speak on the proposed
annexation of over 1,200 acres. Let's
think about it. 1,200 acres. That's a
lot. For months, the citizens of
Cheyenne have stood at this podium, that
podium, and sat in all of these chairs.
We have voiced consistent and growing
concerns. We are losing the soul of our
community to an unchecked and explosion
of growth since I can't say data centers
apparently.
You've heard us speak on the strain to
our power grid, our neighborhoods, the
depletion of our water tables, the
rising costs that yes, we all actually
see right now. So, you can tell us we're
not paying for it, but my bill's gone up
every month in the last 12 months. How
about yours? Yours, too. Yeah, I know.
The plan to move west on Happy Jack Road
is a line in the sand that should not be
crossed. This isn't just vacant land.
This area is the gateway to our natural
beauty. It is adjacent to the High
Plains Arborum, a site of historical and
ecological significance. It is a
corridor where our wildlife still roams
free and where the horizon isn't yet
dominated by industrial cooling towers
and gray concrete boxes. By pushing
industrial development into this
specific area, you are not just growing
the city. You are destroying the very
landscape that makes Wyoming Wyoming.
We are sacrificing our fuse shield, our
tranquility, and our natural heritage
for a handful of permanent jobs and tax
revenue that cannot buy back a destroyed
ecosystem once it's gone. We're told
this is progress, but progress that
annoy ignores the will of the governed
is not leadership. It's a breach of
trust. While companies like Microsoft
and Meta announced multi-billion dollar
expansions, the people living in the
county pockets and the surrounding rural
areas are left to deal with the noise,
the light pollution, and the fear that
their wells will run dry. This body was
elected to represent the citizens of
Cheyenne, not the interests of Silicon
Valley. We the people are telling you
again today that this form of growth is
unacceptable and unwanted. I want to be
very clear. We are watching. We are
documenting these votes. And we will
continue to fight this expansion with
every tool available to us. If you
continue to refuse to listen to the
people who actually live here, then you
are making a choice. And in November,
those citizens that you refuse to listen
to will make theirs. We will remember
who stood for the beauty of our lands
and who sold it off. We urge you to vote
no on this annexation and finally put
the residents of Cheyenne first. Thank
you. Thank you, Miss McCoy.
Heather Madrid again. Um
I'm here to oppose the proposed
annexation and eventual reszoning of the
1200 plus acres of Cockrants Ranch
property. Um, this owner petitioned
annexation involves land that is only
just over 5%
contiguous to existing city limits,
which hardly makes it make sense to the
rest of it is surrounded by the county.
So, the five plus% barely constitutes as
a logical next step.
Um,
the request would reszone all these
1,200 plus acres to business park
classification.
Public records and city staff
presentations confirm that this zoning
would allow uses including data data
centers, which has now been confirmed.
Um, that that's exactly what's going to
happen. The vast majority
um,
back up. Sorry. Uh many residents across
Cheyenne in the region have expressed
concerns about the rapid growth of data
centers in our communities. The vast
majority of the rolling hills community
and surrounding neighborhoods have
raised concerns about potential traffic
noise and a permanent disruption to
their quality and way of life.
Proposed massive industrial parks of
unprecedented size and scale should not
be approved using standard regulations.
This is far from standard economic
development. regulations need to be
further updated to ensure the long-term
health, safety, and sustainability of
our communities. I urge the public
service committee and city council to
council to reject this annexation and
resoning. Um, additionally, I can
appreciate the closed loop theory. Um,
we have yet to see that play out in
practice. However, the water is only one
of many natural resources that we have
here. I worry about uh the air and um
there's a natural gas fired power plant
going to um power the project jade. What
are my lungs going to look like in 10
years after all these projects continue
to be approved? What about people who
already have respiratory issues? This
goes beyond the water table. This goes
beyond the cost. This is our long-term
health and lives. I want my kids to grow
up health and healthy and safe and their
and my grandchildren to grow up the
same. This is enough. There have been so
many of these um projects approved
rapidly without without having proper
regulations in place. And I would like
we we need to push pause before we just
continue to be landlocked in data
centers. Nobody wants that. Nobody.
Except for
the developers, of course. Thank you.
Thank you. Other comments.
Go ahead.
Afternoon. I'm Jane Leinger. I have a
property in Ward One and I live out on
HappyJack.
I believe the following is a true
statement. the city when it is
considering property annexation within
the city limits. Consider different
criteria and circumstances than when
they're considering proposed annexation
of property owner when the land or
property exists outside the city limits.
With regard to the Cox annexation, there
are certainly criteria if the property
were to be in the city that meet the
criteria in the staff report. However,
the Cox annexation,
excuse me, I'm dry or any property
outside the city limits deserves many
additional criteria considerations not
only for the present but for the future
and into the next possible 40 75 years
as we heard somebody lives had lived out
there for 40 years that go beyond the
financial reward to the city or to the
property owner.
He mentioned he was from Arizona and
property in Arizona. Rural areas could
be
rural areas um regulations could be
considered here. Arizona has extreme
water issues among other environmental
impacts. One of Arizona's criteria
pertains to natural waterways andor
topography
waterways. Those areas are not to be
disturbed and there's one out there. The
out of the city limits and the general
lay of the land is a situation with the
Cox annexation.
Does the natural topography not found in
the city deserve our attention to
protect above ground vegetation, animal
habitat from small prairie animals to
birds, fox, analopee. I'm sure Rolling
Hills residents have seen other animals
besides horses and cattle. also natural
waterways above and below ground of
which are likely the source for water
for rolling hills wells.
This is a list of points of
consideration. Of course, we've
mentioned the mortuary. There's the
noise consideration.
There's traffic. There's construction.
Increased load on the road, which is a
county road and not a commercial bedded
road. um access to the walking path from
Rolling Hills across to the north uh
uh park area. The topography that is
rolling now and has a depression in it
uh for natural waterway underneath and
above ground would be made flat. There's
animal life habitat. There's the value
of having that present. the water um
purity and the volume of water and any
water pollution from just additional
traffic out there of automobiles and and
uh general watering of the grass or
whatever they plan to do for landscaping
and fertilizing. There's the quality of
life property issues such as loss of the
value
of the view to the west.
>> Thank you.
>> I like where I am and that's quick and I
have a bunch more Thank you.
>> Hi, my name is Barbara Heritage and I
live in Rolling Hills and um I am asking
the city of Cheyenne to please not annex
this area. Um the sale of the property
is determined on putting in an having it
annexed and putting in a data center. Um
I am asking that you please table this
uh annexation for the data center. Um
because there are nine states that have
put a moratorum on data centers.
>> Ma'am, please keep it to the annexation
not the data center.
The land is
>> but this is about the annexation.
>> Well, the annexation is going to
contribute to traffic on H Happyjack
which is getting even with the growth
out beyond
uh that that road is really becoming
very dangerous. Um and also there um
this area that is not conducive
and if it were to put houses out there
that would be a different story. But um
I think everybody here is is um asking
you to table this until you can find out
the environmental reports on this
property.
and um maybe down the road um go ahead
and have another meeting to uh discuss
annexation after you have the reports
for the environment
etc. traffic, schools, etc. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Madam Chairman. Rick Kessler. I live in
Rolling Hills. we kind of got to talk
about data centers because that's how we
started was with data centers. So then
we moved to annexation.
But anyway, I guess I'm a little bit
dismayed because yes, the city did
notify property owners, but out of over
200 property owners that are going to be
impacted by this annexation by my
calculations, and I'm not very good at
the high math, but three properties were
notified. the Shellback Ranch, the Cox
Ranch, and the King Ranch.
Those are the only properties that are
within 300 feet of this annexation.
So, and you'll know all those are
ranches. You didn't notify any
businesses. There's no business on the
north side of HappyJack. It's all range
land or residential. There's no
commercial or industrial activity at
all.
So the state statute says that an
annexation of the area is for the
protection of the health, safety and
welfare of the persons residing in the
area. So I want to know how does this
protect my health, safety and welfare.
Is increased light good for me? The
increased noise good for me? Is the
increased traffic good for me? I don't I
don't think so.
It also says that the the area should
constitute a natural, geographical and
economical and social part of the
annexing city or town. So what part of
this rangeand which has been a ranch for
over
126 27 years maybe 130 years fit that
description? It doesn't. It's all ranch
land. Everything around it is ranch
land. the ranch, Shellback Ranch to the
north, the Polo Ranch, even right south
of of uh uh the Cox property is the King
Ranch. So, there's no there's no
commercial or industrial activity. So,
we already tolerate the noise and light
from the North Range Business Park. Um I
have to walk out and listen to the DA
Bitcoin data mining facility.
That sounds like a C130 ramping up to
take off and I'm two two miles away from
that. So,
I don't know that this is going to be of
any benefit to any of us. Um, you know,
this is a historic ranch. 50 years ago,
Mark T. Cox III told me that I'd never
have to worry about any development to
the West. His son, William Sterling Cox,
by all accounts was an outdoor
outdoorsman, an avid outdoorsman and
conservation conservationist.
So, Mrs. Black and even Jeff can
probably speak to this better than I
can, but I have to think that that's
probably what he thought, too. Thank
you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Good afternoon, members of the
committee. My name is Dante Rushton and
I am the director of real estate and
property management for Cheyenne Leads.
Uh I just wanted to speak a little bit
about the proposed annexation as it
relates to business parks. Um one big
note is annexation is a tool made
available to property owners to utilize
to meet uh certain aspects of property
rights such as use and enjoyment. And so
this further constitutes what staff has
demonstrated in the staff report that
what this annexation is proposing meets
those merits of health, safety and
welfare. So this applicant can connect
to city services of such as water,
sewer, fire and police services. And as
mentioned in the city staff report, uh
in 2024, North Ranger Business Park, one
of those in which we manage was annexing
the city. And that is a great service to
offer to property owners having access
to things such as police service and
fire. We're we benefit from having
police presence in our business park to
mitigate uh concerns with crime. And so
that's just one thing to know is
annexation is a tool to help. And then
on the note of just the health, safety
and welfare business parks as a whole to
further embody the health, safety and
welfare, they operate under what are
private covenants or CCNRs. And so those
are private restrictions of land use to
help mitigate potential conflicts with
residential areas specifically. So in a
business park typically you do not allow
residential uses. They are set up for
small and light industrial uses to
provide compatible land use planning.
And so that's one of the benefits of a
business park too is the private
regulation of land use to help further
embody that health, safety and welfare
aspect that has to be met through the
statute. So thank you. Thank you,
>> Mr. Galotus.
>> Good afternoon, Sam Gallotus. Thank you
for the opportunity. Um, for the record,
um, Madame Chair, you know, mentioning
data centers is the intended purpose of
this annexation. So, I think it's a
little unfair for not letting people
speak about it, but that's not what I'm
here to speak about today. Um the other
evening I expressed uh both a surprise
and a lack of understanding of how this
annexation it's in its shape, its intent
and everything really fits into the area
that it's targeted for right now. Um and
so I've been searching for what is the
guiding light? What is the planning
criteria you and the county are using to
determine where all these things are
going? Okay. And lo and behold, I went
and I I referenced plan sh. Okay. Uh
right off your website. It, you know,
very succinctly, you know, lays out a
very uniform
uh border for the area that it covers.
Um and it the whole thing in the
beginning talks about that this is the
guiding light for where growth will
happen over the next 10 to 20 years and
that it's an integrated city and county
master plan and the plan serves as a
tool for the city of Cheyenne, Larry
County and the MO. And then it goes on
to talk about how this plan serves as a
tool to help inform residents, property,
and business owners and other
stakeholders about the shared community
vision for the future. I would state
again, my surprise is this does not fit
into the area, the intended purpose or
the annexation. And we talk about how
the people's plan and it goes through
plan Cheyenne and talks about how
important the public's input and
feedback is and everything else. And
then I finally get to the point where
it, you know, the plan was established
in 20 or 2006 and it was revised in
2014.
And it and it basically states that it
should be updated every 5 years. And the
reason that it says it should be updated
every 5 years is because you got to keep
pace with the times. Right now, it looks
like we're 10 years behind schedule in
updating this plan. And when you
consider all the things that have been
going on, um it it needs to be updated.
So I would ask why has it not been
updated? Why has the public not been
involved in all these changes that are
taking place? And then it goes on to
talk about the review steps. And one of
the things it talks about is the
developer should schedule a neighborhood
meeting to discuss the project with area
property owners prior to bringing the
proposal to the planning commission. It
goes on to state that both the county
commission and the city council should
approve amendments in whatever way,
shape, or form to the plan. So, I would
ask, has the Larmy County Commission
approved this plan? Why was the
neighborhood not notified in advance?
And why has there not been any updates?
Lastly, I would just say that all of the
opinions that have been given uh no
offense to staff as to why uh this meets
criteria are opinions. They are not
fact.
>> Um and so they can all be debated. So I
would strongly suggest that you go back
to the drawing board on this because you
haven't even followed your own plan.
Otis,
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
my name is Seth with the City of Shine
Planning and Development Department. Uh,
a few commenters have raised some good
points that I'd like to address real
fast. Um, one is the comprehensive plan
hasn't been updated in 10 years. Like to
note for everyone present that we
currently have an RFP out to to update
that plan because we've recognized that
it hasn't been updated. So, we hope to
update it within the next year or two.
hopefully setting some new guidelines
for development. I think RFP
specifically mentions data centers so
that we can inter
inter engage with the community as a
whole on um data center development and
what's appropriate. Um secondly, this
project does include a future land use
map amendment. However, it has not been
submitted yet because as we discussed
with the previous project that I was up
here for, future land use maps only
require one hearing in front of the um
council. So that will be introduced and
that will set the stage for data center
development. So I encourage everyone who
has concerns about
industrial zoning,
business park zoning, development of
data center or other types of uses to be
talking to those items that are going to
be coming up. So we have the zone change
coming up and we have a future land use
map amendment that will be coming onto
the agenda.
speaking to the annexation as a as an
item all on its own. Um, without a zone
change being requested, we would be
looking at potentially or the future
land use map amendment being requested.
We'd be looking at the potential for
residential development here. Would it
be appropriate for all options on the
table, whether it be industrial, whether
it be single family homes, would those
be um appropriate in this area? When
we're talking the annexation, we have to
look at all potential options under
annexation. Then when it comes to zone
change and that future landings use map
amendment spec more specific, we get
finer grained as to what those options
might be.
>> Um, thank you for your time. I hope that
clarifies a few things.
>> Sir,
>> thank you, Madam Chairman. I'm Steve
Johnson. I'm a resident of uh Laram
County. And there's a few things that
I'd like to bring to your knowledge. One
is life safety. You say knife life
safety constantly on every annexation
you've you've produced and I would like
to ask where what residents are going to
be in this data center that your life
safety is so important to. The other
thing you know I've been to a few of
your city council meetings. I can't vote
for you. I'm in the county
but I think you have a budget problem.
Everything I've heard of is you're
chasing money. You're chasing the tax
dollars that this data center is going
to produce. You cannot produce. You
don't have enough money for a city park
of 75 acres. You have a you don't even
know if you can you can provide for a 65
acre park uh city park. You were going
to expand Waltersite to five lanes. You
still haven't found money for that. So,
I think you need to put this whole thing
on hold. do a budget. Every item on your
agenda, every time you meet should have
a cost to the citizens how much this is
going to cost me as a as a homeowner in
Cheyenne. And I would like to one one
more thing if I could ask the crowd
here, how many people are from the city
of Cheyenne that think that this is the
they need to have this annexation. It's
going to make my my uh life in Cheyenne
more enjoyable.
Is there anybody
I would I would like to ask how many
people are from the county that are
really concerned about this issue? And
that's all I want to ask. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir. Any other public
comments in the room,
Mr. White?
>> Madame Chairman, through you, uh,
Michael White. Um,
I'm a sixth generation member of uh,
resident of Lurman County. I've lived in
this county for almost eight decades.
I say no to annexation.
We talk about life safety. Well, let's
talk a little bit about that.
Currently, Larry County has sheriff's
service out there for our law
enforcement. We have a highway
department that takes care of the road
into this project.
We also have water and sewer that could
be available without even annexing this,
but we haven't even really heard all the
data except we hear the percentages of
that.
Um, in addition, we have a
fire station that's right next door to
us that's actually farther away than the
fire station on Roundtop.
We also we have all the services that
anybody needs out there. I share with
Mr. Gallotus as far as what is the real
use of this land. It's been a ranch ever
since I can remember.
Last point I'd like to bring up is that
we had an individual that's an attorney
in our town and also the attorney
general at one time and she said we have
some issues with county pockets and I
agree with her.
I respect Mr. Connor. I have never sat
down with anybody from the board of
public utilities to say where in writing
are they asking this piece of property
adjacent to the other piece of property
that you need to have annexed. I've not
heard anything from Mr.
uh the director which he has expressed
some stuff to me personally. If we're
going to know what's going on here, we
need to know those calculations for
annexation. So, I strongly suggest that
we either table this or vote against it.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. White.
Miss Woodhouse.
>> Good afternoon, Madame Chairman, members
of the committee. Um, I repres Gay
Woodhouse. I represent Cox Farms. Yes,
I have some I have some handouts here.
And wait a minute. Okay. All right. Um,
I want to introduce this topic by saying
that I think that my clients Cox Ranch
LLC and and especially Beverly Cox Black
and her brother Mark T.
were kind of duped into selling this
latest that 44 acres that caused the
contiguity between the North Park uh and
North Range Park and this annexation to
create some the 5% of of contiguity. I
mean that was just done in December. The
reason that their name was included in
the first applications on all the
documents that we received for all these
different matters was because they had
owned that until December of 2025.
I think that this was a was a plan that
they were not told about. I'm sure so
that the value that they received for
that was nowhere near what it should
have been. And it was done for the
purpose of creating a fictional
annexation, a fictional contiguity.
This is, you know, the the fact that
it's now being said that it doesn't
matter that it's only 5.62%
contiguity is because it has the city
when the city is way up at the end of it
and has been sitting out there forever
without being annexed. So I really think
that they have been taken advantage of
in a number of different ways and
especially regarding this mausoleum.
They originally gave this part of the
property to the brother uh William S.
Cox with the mausoleum on it with an
understanding this is a family
mausoleum. William S. Cox is buried
there and what that they would have an
easement that there would be no nothing
would ever endanger that nothing would
ever impair their ability to visit their
the mausoleum. It's you know I'm showing
these I can't I don't I'm sorry I don't
have a picture for everybody but you
know I I I'll go through each one of
these pictures. You know the first one
is the mausoleum. It's it's about 22
feet wide square and 20 to 22 feet tall
tall. It's it's marble that was imported
by Mrs. Cox for when her husband Mark T.
Cox III died so that they could be um he
didn't want to be buried in the ground.
He wanted to be buried on this
mausoleum. And in particular, he wanted
to be buried on this hill because that
was the hill where he used to go up when
he was a little boy and look down at the
water features and all the land that you
know is so beautiful out there that
everyone's been talking about.
The second picture is another picture
just of shows how big it really is.
And the other pictures are the caskets
that are in there. Just two of the uh
four that are in there, but there are
two of the more recent ones. One is of
Mrs. Cox who was buried in 22, and the
one with the flower is is William S.
Cox. That's his casket. There's also a
picture of uh the the names of the other
Cox relatives, the walkers who also have
caskets in there as well. And then
there's an urn which is again as is a
walker relative.
Um
when after we brought this up on Monday
night, we received notification
immediately from the Cox people, William
S. Cox trust people saying, "Oh, they
were willing to do an agreement to move
the mausoleum."
So, we received that agreement and
Jennifer, can I give that to
First of all, I want to tell you, oh my
gosh. Um, I want to tell you this this
agreement
is nothing more than a promise to have
them arbitrate at their own cost
to have the things done that should be
done for this property. It they say that
it's erns. There's only one urn in
there. These are bodies in caskets that
are in this mausoleum. This is a
twotrack road that goes from the edge
of, you know, the house that you see out
on HappyJack Road up to the mausoleum,
which you can also see from HappyJack
Road. It go It's a twotrack lane. It
goes down and through a water feature
that doesn't have water in it right now,
and then up onto the hill. And for to
move it, 130 tons, 230 tons, I I don't
have any idea. but to move it and then
make us have to pay for an arbitrator
where they have already designated the
arbitrator will be Judge Murphy. No
other arbitrators. They're telling us
who we have to deal with when they don't
want to do this later. And we have no
promise from the ultimate purchaser that
they would honor this. All they have to
say is, "Hey, we sold it." Tough, tough,
tough luck.
So, I'm done with my time, but this is
not an easy situation and it's very
heartfelt that their concern over their
mausoleum. Thank you.
>> Hi. Hi. Again, Jack O'Neal. Um, so we
again learned of this last Monday and I
know there's a lot of emotions between
the families involved and a lot of
history as well and uh we do not have
all of the history but we want to make
sure that we will lean in 110% to bring
any resolution. I have not seen nor has
Tom seen whatever document y'all are
holding now. Um, but I can say 110%
um, we'll either give them the land and
a permanent easement for the longevity
of, you know, record it with the uh,
with the city and the county or whether
that's paying to move it or whatever
solution they would like to find. We
will 110% want to be great partners and
I don't know what is in that agreement,
but would love to see it at some point,
but just know that that did not come
from us.
>> Thank you.
Jane Leser again. I think this might
also be a different conversation if the
property being annexed was being
considered for some sort of large
property ranchets. Um, one thing I'd
like people to consider, I think rolling
hills would consider HappyJack like a
fire boundary or a major boundary line
that anything south of HappyJack to
being developed would be a different
issue than anything north of HappyJack.
and all the criteria or all the concerns
from the citizens that have been
mentioned. I have a thought for the city
council
because the county roads out there are
just that. They're county roads and uh I
maybe a better uh proposition would be
to extend County Road 222 south of I 80
and connect it with Swan Ranch and put
your data center out there. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
Mr. Ketchum.
heavy on the mister.
Madame chair, members of the uh city
council, uh thank you for having this
hearing. Uh
first of all, in my entire lifetime, I
never thought I'd ever see this happen.
We're taking,240 acres, two sections of
lands out of agriculture, which impacts
Sam Galotas, impacts the King Ranch, all
the ranches that are contiguous to this.
That's going to impact their agriculture
tremendously. especially their grazing
situation. So, for that reason, I'm
totally against annexation, the
annexation of the property. There's
other business parks already annexed
that could have more data centers. So,
if they want to put a data center,
there's plenty of places to go. They
don't have to go right there in my
opinion. Uh, also that that ranch right
there, it's a historic ranch as pointed
out by Mr. Kesler. The ranch has been
there since 1897. something like that.
And the first Angus that ever come to
this country were put on that ranch and
it was called the Wyoming Angus Ranch.
Pedigree Angus first ones ever here had
sales there where the little buyer
always got the big welcome that was
right on the side of the barn.
But anyway, I hate to see this happen.
Uh the owner, his name is Cox. Not
related to these Coxes. Not related to
these Coxes whatsoever. He assured us
when he got this property that it would
never be anything but grazing. So he
lied to us for one thing. Now he's got a
developer from Texas or Arizona. Hell,
who knows where they're from. And what I
would suggest is let's have a let let if
they want to be good neighbors, let's
have a meeting with all the neighbors
before we even talk about annexation to
find out exactly what they are going to
do because I have no clue. At least the
cat's out of the bag. It's a data center
so we know that. I guess I can't talk
about that. But anyway, I agree with Mr.
Gallotus and all the people that spoke
here today.
>> Thank you, Mr. Ketchum.
>> I'm sorry, Sam Gallotus. Again, I won't
take a lot of time, but three minutes is
short. Um, I I just want to draw back
again this is not a logical addition to
this part of the country. Okay, that is
a very important issue. The second thing
is
this pl we're not even following plan
Cheyenne.
This is the guiding light is where where
I've come from. You're not following
plan Cheyenne. In fact, you're
squiggling out this huge $1,200 or 1,200
acre annexation and tacking it onto the
side of it. That type of thing should
have been laid out far in advance for
people to absorb and talk about and the
pros and cons of it. So, uh, I don't see
that you followed your own guiding light
and and that negatively impacts the
public. And so, again, I would stress to
consider these things. There's all the
other things about data centers and all
that, but this is not a logical addition
to this territory. And you haven't even
followed what you've put in. And you've
gone 10 years without doing an update to
the plan. And all of these things are
going on around us. Why have we not done
the updates, two of them, by now? So,
and we probably wouldn't be here if that
were the case. So, I just I had to come
back. Thank you.
>> Okay. And I think we have some people
online, correct?
Uh, Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Madame Chair, members of the committee,
my name is Charles Miller. I'm speaking
exclusively to items 18, 19, and 20
regarding the Cox Ranch annexation and
business park resoning. Before I address
the annexation itself, I must formally
state for the official record that the
legal validity of this entire hearing is
now severely compromised. Madam Chair,
moments ago, you interrupted a Laramie
County citizen and actively attempted to
chill their speech by stating that this
hearing is quote not about data centers.
Yet just prior to that, you allowed the
developer, Tom Glymmeer, and a private
lobbyist from Cheyenne Leadeds to speak
extensively and without interruption
about their data center plans, their
corporate awards, and their specific
water usage metrics. Under the first
amendment of the United States
Constitution, a city council public
comment period constitutes a limited
public forum. It is illegal to engage in
viewpoint discrimination. You cannot
allow a developer to justify an
annexation using his business plan and
then place a gag order on the taxpayers
when they attempt to discuss the
infrastructural impact impacts of that
same exact business same business plan.
By selectively chilling public
participation, you are violating
procedural due process and the
transparency mandates of the Wyoming
Public Meetings Act, statute 16443.
If you proceed to advance this
annexation after actively silencing the
opposition while granting free reign to
the proponents, you risk rendering this
entire proceeding legally invalid and
highly vulnerable to to uh judicial
review. Regarding the Cox Ranch
annexation itself, it is it
fundamentally fails the statutory test.
Under Wyoming State Statute 15142, an
annexation must be for the protection of
the health, safety, and welfare of the
persons residing in the area. Your own
staff admitted out loud today that the
city already provides fire and police
response to this area due to the North
Range Business Park. If the emergency
response capacity already exists, then
the public safety narrative is a sham.
It is a recycled administrative pretext
used to shroud what is actually an owner
initiated commercial land grab. Let's
look at the facts. This 1250 acre parcel
has a legally bare minimum 5.26%
contiguity to existing city limits. It
is a peninsula peninsula surrounded by
the county. The only reason that this
annexation is before you is because it
is the mechanism to execute item 20, the
immediate reasonzoning of this
agricultural land into a business park.
But where is the data to protect the
public welfare? Where is the
environmental impact study? There is no
independent hydraological audit in your
packet today to back up the developer
claims about water usage. Furthermore,
where is the road maintenance agreement?
Building a 12,200 acre industrial park
will require thousands of heavy hall
construction trips. We have residents
testifying today that nearby roads are
already failing. Yet there are no
pavement impact fees attached to this
annexation. By advancing this today, you
are asking taxpayers to sign a blank
check to subsidize industrial water use
and road degradation, all while actively
violating the public's right to speak
freely in this chamber. I urge
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller.
>> Thank you.
>> Um just a minute, ma'am. We have one
other person online that's been waiting
a really long time.
>> Mr. Epler, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you. Can you hear me? My name is
Reeba Eper.
>> Yes.
>> Thank you. I'm an attorney and I've been
friends with Beverly Cox and her family
for a long time. My family leased that
ranch for at least 10 years from when I
was a teenager into my 20s. I've spent a
lot of time there and I would like to
point out that it's a very uh
hydraologically significant area to the
city of Cheyenne and it provides a huge
benefit in terms of recharge to the
aquafer and to the city of Cheyenne's
wellfields. Uh there is a study that was
done in 1967
by the USGS and it's called Lowry and
Christrist and it's a study of uh a lot
of Laramie County but this specific part
is found on page 31 and it states that
Crow Creek at one time was perennial
from the mountains to the vicinity of
Arc Colola which is just west of there
and south and it's citing Foley 1943
and Babco Babcock and Borland
But the channel through the city
Wellfield is now dry. And it shows how
the city of Cheyenne Wells in 1967
had already caused Crow Creek to go dry
due to groundwater pumping. And
the um there's another study that I'd
like to point you to and it was done by
a gentleman named Ben Jordan and he did
the city of Cheyenne's Wellfield
Protection Plan um as his thesis talking
about how the the toxins from the um
missiles the MX missiles west of there
are drawn to the city of Cheyenne's
wellfield by virtue of pumping. And so I
would like to to state that this will
have a significant negative impact on
the city of Cheyenne's water supply
because it will increase the demand on
those wellfields. Um and I find that to
be an unacceptable
um it actually is detrimental to the
public safety welfare of the area. In
addition, these types of developments
don't require the type of review that
would be um adequate in terms of the um
doing a hydraological study. I I know
for a fact there are eagle's nests out
there as well as um other raptors nests.
There are endangered plants such as the
uh Utes Ladies Truss and the um Colorado
butterfly plant on that crow. When I was
walking there at a party last summer, I
found numerous tepee rings really near
the mausoleum that will be destroyed. I
know of other Indian graves and other
significant cultural sites out there
will be destroyed in this as well as
there's another graveyard that hasn't
been discussed and that is there's a
house on the north end of this ranch the
northeast end of this ranch where other
people are buried and I believe that's a
Ketchum um cemetery. So I think that
that will be um another cemetery that
will be um impacted as well. Therefore,
I I think that because the impact of the
hydraology of the area by covering it in
pavement, you are going to have an
actual negative impact to the health and
safety welfare of the area that um
therefore this annexation should not be
approved.
>> Thank you, Miss Kepler.
>> Go ahead.
>> K McAdams and through the chair, please.
I'd like to address the issue of please
don't annex
I don't know who provided this, but we
weren't allowed to talk about data
centers.
I don't know whose brochure, but I
picked it up right here before I came to
the ME meeting and read, so I thought I
could speak to it. Also, if you decide
to annex,
it would be nice because we've
complained now about we don't have funds
for this, we don't have funds for that.
Well, G,
a single large, I won't say the word,
can involve hundreds of millions,
sometimes billions of dollars in
equipment.
And under Wyoming's exemptions,
most of the equipment is not subject to
usage tax, which means they bring in
every six years more equipment that
could have been taxed, but on the back
of this, they brought in what they're
doing in property tax. There's many,
many more dollars. So if we're going to
lose our environment, the continuity of
life to whatever comes into this
annexation,
at least we should be compensated
adequately.
>> Thank you, Miss McAdams.
>> Thank you.
>> Hey, anybody? Yes, Mr. Kesler.
>> One last time, Madam Chairman. Sorry.
>> That's right. Um, after hearing the
testimony, um, I would encourage you to
vote no on this annexation. This is a
historic ranch. I think it was
established about 1896 or 1897.
And, uh, it it's not William Cox or Bill
Cox that's that's petitioning. It's it's
a guy from Florida that's doing this.
Maybe he's never even been to Wy. I
mean, I don't know. He's a lawyer. it.
So anyway, what I would encourage is
rather than an annexation and talking
about uh business parks and data centers
that is that we should be talking about
historic preservation. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Hello, my name's Rob Burns, uh, Rolling
Hills Estates. I'll just ask you to vote
no on this annexation. Obviously,
there's a lot of problems with it and uh
that's all I got. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Anybody else online? Jennifer.
>> Uh Maj, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Hi, my name is Mandy Shadic. I'm out in
Rolling Hills.
Um, I'm asking you to vote no on
annexation and my reasons here uh very
much align with my neighbors. Obviously,
the city doesn't have enough funds and
they haven't done studies on impact to
see how it will actually affect the
neighborhood and the pocket does exist
if this happens which is going to force
negative impact upon people who chosen
to establish outside of city on purpose.
Um I think we are giving too much to out
ofate private development. When we look
further into Via West Group uh it leads
to Flexen Flexaw which is a Morgan
Stanley Infrastructure
uh subsidiary which is dealing in
acquisitions of property and investment
in property. It's very weird to me that
we keep outsourcing so much to people
and corporations that don't actually
live here. And we could have better
solutions. We could keep that land
agriculture and we could build green
houses out there that could very much
have a positive impact not only on the
community that is rural but in the city.
But it seems to me that Wyoming is
trying to take away agriculture, which
is very sad. Um, I think that we have
some smooth talk talking investors
obviously coming in and they don't even
know exactly what they're talking about
because they are mediaries to these
other bigger corporations. They just
have to come in here with a pretty face
and say the right thing. But I um
applaud my neighborhood and the people
of the city who are willing to speak up
on these topics. I think that if we
really want to be Wyoming and support
local business,
this should be one of the reasons why
this annexation is a no for me. Thank
you.
>> Thank you,
>> council. This is Tom Gmer again of West
Group. We are not affiliated with Morgan
Stanley. Um I just want to clarify that
we're a private company um with three
partners.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Okay.
Anybody else?
>> Could you hit that green button, please?
>> I'm Jana Tolman. I don't live in the
Rolling Hills area. I do live in the
city of Cheyenne, but one of the things
that all Wyoming knights appreciate is
the landscape. And if you take that
away, you pretty much take away Wyoming.
And
um you know, I think these people who
have lived here for years and years and
years, they don't want to be ousted.
They don't want, you know, people coming
in. I'd love to see, like you said,
something that comes from our community
that will benefit our community, not
something from outside that somehow
we're going to try to make the community
benefit from
and take away from those are already
benefiting in the community.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
Anybody else?
Okay, I'm going to close public comment
then
committee. Can I get a motion and a
second?
>> Dr. Renie,
>> we need to have a motion on the floor to
discuss it. So, I'll move to
approve on second.
>> And do we have a second?
>> Second.
>> Okay. So, Dr. Renie moved and uh
Councilman Layborn seconded. Um do we
have any discussion from the committee?
>> Chairwoman Emmens, I do.
>> Go ahead, Dr. Al.
>> Um I just I have a few questions. One is
uh we heard about environmental reports.
I wasn't aware that those have even been
ordered. Does anybody know if
environmental reports have been ordered
or requested at all?
Anybody?
>> Council members Tom Glaran. Yes, we have
ordered environmental reports. Okay.
>> Thank you. And then my next question um
chairwoman is is the my understanding
was is I had told that a cell had been
completed but I heard someone say that
this was contingent upon um the approval
for annexation.
So, I'm wondering if if the sale is
complete or if it is still waiting uh
and contingent upon this approval. Sorry
to make you make several trips.
>> The sale is not complete.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dr. Alrich. Any other
questions? Okay, Dr. Renie.
Yeah, Madam Chair, I I at least want to
address the water portion of this um
because there's been a lot of discussion
of that. If if they're part of the if
they're on the city water system, then
there is no impact on the water table.
Um in addition, I've had people have
told me or talked to me about um the
fact that our water rates are going up
and they're blaming that on the use of
the data centers, but and I know Mr.
Strong's in the audience, so he'll
correct me if I'm wrong, but when the
when the refinery converted to bofuels,
I think we lost sales of about a million
gallons a day and we had anticipated
that the data centers would make up that
use. They have not made up that use.
Matter of fact, we currently use about
the same amount of water that we used in
Cheyenne that we used 14 or 15 years
ago. So while the cost for the board of
public I mean currently to to lay pipe
is about $350 a foot I believe um their
costs have gone up over over that 14 or
15 years significantly as all of our
costs have and yet their revenue is
still about where it was 14 or 15 years
ago because data centers are not using
water. Um, that's more likely why our
our costs have been going up because
we're not selling the water that we
anticipated that we would.
>> Uh, other
>> Did you have a question for me?
>> No, I just want to say if I if my
statement was inaccurate, I knew you
were here and would be able to correct
me.
>> Okay. Other discussion from the
committee,
Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um
this is a
>> a matter that requires more thought. Um
this is a lot of things have come up uh
at this meeting
that uh didn't come up at the public
hearing at the last council meeting.
key amongst them uh Madame Chairman is
the indisputable fact
that this is about a data center and to
say that the annexation
is not about a data center
really makes us look at this process as
being
in need of reform I guess you could say
or
some sort of better understanding
because
if this was the case and this was the
intent,
um why are we learning about it today?
And we got some information from the
planning office today that uh talked
about it. Um I think that that's really
not the best.
I handed to the other members of the
committee here a
map that we uh got
Mr. Wolf and I got from the Board of
Public Utilities staff this morning that
spelled out that arc of
data centers that runs from this area
south Cheyenne and then off to the east.
And what we're really talking about here
is something that I think was brought up
in this testimony earlier that this is
how do we plan for this type of growth?
How do we plan and evaluate
uh these situations? because there are
many many factors that come into play
here and actually I think it's safe to
say there are many data centers planned
and some data centers uh are talking
about their own power source which is
another factor and so I I really believe
that what we should do here is postpone
this for at least two weeks to allow
some of these issues issues to be
clarified. The mausoleum
is uh certainly an incredibly unique
but uh nevertheless important factor and
if there's some resolution that can be
acquired about that so be it. When I
look at this map here, um I there's a
factor here that I think is of supreme
importance that hasn't been discussed
yet and that is the fact that the wash
water that comes out of our Sherard
treatment plant and we can see it on our
map. It runs uh from what was the old
plant right across the road and then
down right across this property.
And that's the water that recharges Crow
Creek. And I'm not to I'm not to say
exactly what uh is going to happen here,
but
that's going to continue. That's the way
that we
uh clean our water and distribute it
into town. And this wash water is uh
basically what recharges Crow Creek
today. So that's a factor I think we
need some more uh understanding of. I
think that there's just a lot of things
here that uh could benefit from
discussion and understanding the issue
been raised here. Um I understand
that people want to develop their land
as they believe is appropriate. I
understand that uh there is a um data
centers in the vicinity and a business
park basically across the street.
All of these things make for a difficult
discussion.
Nevertheless, a very important one. So I
think that uh there have been enough
questions raised here and I I think it's
really important that we don't let the
technicalities
and in some of these cases we've heard
some testimony about
legal questions that I don't believe
apply here
but there are there is the question is
this process that we're in in working on
right now really clear to the people who
are involved
and really understandable in light of an
absolutely to me
unbelievable and
unprecedented
boom.
Excuse me.
I I kind of compare this to some of the
things that have happened in Wyoming,
not around here, but certainly in the
Powder River Basin or the overthrust
belt way out west when uh those energy
development situations happened and grew
so fast and had such a difficult time
for people to adjust and and develop.
And um we've had discussion here about
the financial benefits that uh are a big
part of this discussion and what the
long-term
uh on and m of these facilities are. So
I believe that uh it would be beneficial
for us to uh take a twoe postponement
really clarify some of these issues and
make a better decision as a result
because
I just want to speak to this personally
if I could.
I really don't like
an understanding that this is about a
data center. we have the public hearing.
It wasn't about the data center
and that wasn't really what was
in the obvious purpose of the public
hearing was for you all and we all to
take a look at those issues and make a
determination. So, I move that we
postpone this uh annexation for two
weeks.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
Re are you waiting for a second?
>> Um, no. I was waiting for your light
because we already have a motion on the
table.
>> Yeah. You need a
>> Yeah. So, you need a second.
>> Do we have a second to do to uh
Councilman Lebornne's me motion?
Okay, that fails.
Um um Chairwoman Amensments for you. The
reason I didn't support that amendment
was because I don't know that a two-eek
postponement is going to it's not going
to change my mind probably. Um and I
don't know that um we're going
anything's going to be found in that
twoe time period. I'm disappointed, I
guess, that I agree with my colleague
from Ward One that we had a public
hearing last Monday night um under
annexation
um but we never talked about what what
was being planned for this area which um
you know is neither neither here nor
there. I I also think that um I took
copious notes while we were talking from
the 21 people that made comments and
some of them multiple times and um
really am concerned about some of the uh
items that were brought up by Reeba Eper
um when she talked about um the water um
issues that my colleague from Ward One
also mentioned, but also about the
historical culture as well as the
sensitivity of um some of the protected
plants. and um things in that area. I am
looking at this map that um my colleague
from W one just gave us before the
meeting that shows all the different
data centers in the uh Laramie County.
I'm looking and there are lots there's a
lot of land left where data centers
could be put and I know it's not it I
know it's not probably the preferred
area. Um, obviously the area that we're
being asked to annex today is the
preferred area, but I'm just I
I wish that uh we had had this had a
conversation with the community and the
neighbors before this was brought
forward u for a public hearing or for
annexation. And um hindsight's always
2020 obviously, but um I'm torn. I
believe in personal property rights, big
believer and defender of those. Um, and
so believe that that the person that
owns this land now has the right to do
what with it what they'd like to um,
which is to sell it. Um, but I don't
want to become complicit with that in
um, impacting negatively the surrounding
homeowners and property owners um, and
their quality of life and their property
values and um, all of those um, concerns
that have been brought forward. Um, so
for that reason, I'm going to be a a no
vote today. Um, I am hopeful that a
community meeting can be held um by the
um individuals who are wanting to
purchase this property. I will tell you
that in a lot of the areas that I've
seen that we have annex where there have
been data centers built um the data
centers have turned out to be good
neighbors and that um have done some
amazing things for the communities and
done some um good um things wet between
themselves and their neighbors. Um, but
I also, um, think that
th this is one of those situations where
maybe this isn't the right place to
place this and maybe the annexation
isn't appropriate for this part of our
community.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> thank you, Madam Chairwoman. I did when
I was talking about water, I did want to
add one more thing. if the city of
Cheyenne is forced to deal with
curtailment. First of all, we get 70% of
our water I think close to that from the
west slope. Um so
um so I worry more about the impact not
of the data centers underwater but the
effect of the Colorado River compact and
any kind of agreement can be made there.
Um it is if the city does have to deal
with curtailment the data centers are
not going to get a break on that. They
will have to face the same restrictions
that the rest of us will have. Um and I
am going to support this. My view of
this is you have a private sale between
a willing buyer and a willing seller and
then you have a private individual is
asking and become part of the city. In
the past, government has not interjected
themselves into those sales and those
equations and I don't think it's
appropriate that we start. So, thank
you.
>> Okay. And I just want to um
def I want to explain the situation
about the amendment and what or about
the annexation and why I handled it the
way I did. My job, which is not a fun
job right now, is to keep us on track
with the intent of the piece of
legislation or the resolution at hand.
And that is just about the annexation.
Um it's not the the annexation wasn't
written as an annexation for a data
center. It was written as an annexation.
So that's why I tried to keep us going
on the annexation issue. So it's not
that I'm that mean, it's just that's my
job as the um the uh chair of this
committee. So I just wanted to be very
clear about that.
Okay. Any further discussion from the
committee?
Okay. So we have a motion and a second.
All those in favor, please say I by
saying I.
>> I
>> and those opposed.
>> No.
>> Okay. So the um
>> we do not.
>> Madam chair, there was a substitute for
this that would clean up names which was
brought up at the public hearing.
>> Does it matter since we just since it
just failed?
>> There would it. Sorry, Madam Chair.
Conor White, Planning and Development
Department. I believe it would still be
of best interest to at least approve the
substitute
because it does clean up the names in
the ordinance.
>> I told you this isn't fun.
>> And so how do we
>> I believe um at least we do have some
people in here that would also probably
appreciate that
>> the ordinance be cleaned up.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to reconsider
the vote on number 18. Can you do that
as person who voted for it? You're the
only one.
>> Um, you're right. I Yes, it has to be
someone that voted in the majority.
>> So,
>> Mr. Labour,
>> Mr. Madame Chairman, in the interest of
um what I see here in the substitute,
which is correcting and explaining some
uh details here that don't really get to
the heart of the matter, but um would
help us proceed with uh whatever
decision is made um on a on a more
accurate basis or ultimately accurate
basis, I guess you can say. Uh I speak
in favor of that reconsideration
so that we can evaluate this substitute
and possibly uh incorporate it into this
uh matter that will be coming before us
uh one day
uh no doubt. So uh um
>> can we second does Okay, got a second.
Um
I think it's pretty clear what we're
trying to do here. Yes.
>> Okay.
>> What? Jennifer,
>> she's
>> We have a motion for reconsideration. I
have Councilman Laybourne as making the
motion and Dr. Aldridge is seconding. Is
that correct?
>> Yes.
>> Thank you.
>> Um would staff like to talk about what
that
>> we need to vote to reconsider first.
>> Okay.
All those in favor of
>> I'd like to make a comment first.
>> Okay. I I am going to vote to reconsider
this because I think that we do need to
have an accurate um piece of legislation
to go forward to Monday night. Um that
should in no way be indicated that I
would vote for this on Monday evening.
>> Got it.
>> Okay. All those in favor, please signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
>> Okay. Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
amend by substitute dated date, Connor.
April 15th.
>> Dated April 15th,
2026.
>> Second. Thank you.
>> Okay. Dr. Ring moved and um Councilman
Leborn seconded
>> now. Do I go back to
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> So,
>> wait.
>> Yes, they do.
>> They do. Yes. We're
>> on the substitute.
>> Yep. Um, yes, that would be a good idea.
>> Okay. Um, hang on, Mr. Miller.
>> Would staff like to talk about what that
includes, please?
>> Yes, Mr. White. Thank you.
>> What did I say?
>> Oh, sorry, Mr. White. Mr. White,
>> Madame Chair, members of the committee,
Conor Way, Planning Development
Department. So, just for clarification
for everybody in here,
there was some errors within the
original ordinance that was being
discussed. Um, it had to do with
basically I'm I can take responsibility
for it. I had the wrong names um in the
ordinance and on some of my documents.
Um, and that was going off of the
assessor and as um
was pointed out, the assessor didn't
update. So, I had the wrong Cox family
within the ordinance. So, this
substitute is basically just to fix the
names. It updates some language in the
ordinance. It makes things clear
throughout the ordinance for the
annexation itself. It also has an
updated annexation map because I did get
a resubmitt with updated um legal
description. So, that's all this um does
is make those amendments, changes out
the name, make sure basically making
sure everything is correct within the
ordinance itself. So, that is what this
amendment is. Um, that's all that would
be discussed with this is just the
amendment to some names. Um, otherwise I
would say this probably just the
amendment gets approved and then you can
do your reconsideration vote and it'll
probably go the same way it just went.
But
>> at least we'll have the names correct.
>> Correct. The names will be correct. The
document will be updated. You'll have
basically a better document going into
next Monday night. That's that's all
this amendment is.
>> Okay. Are there questions for staff?
Okay. Public comment
>> uh through you, Madam Chairman. Mike
White. Um
I guess I got a question of um
was the substitute available available
today to the public. And if it was, I'd
like for it to be read into the record.
Thank you.
So, Madam Chairwoman, this is why we
really need to have the substitute today
so we can make it part of the official
record online. As you know, we don't
publish documents or substitutes that
you guys have not acted on. So, that's
the other reason why it's really
important to do this today is so that we
can post that corrected document online
so that everybody can have it for Monday
night.
So, to answer Mr. for White's question.
It was not posted online because the
body has not acted on it
>> through you, Madam Chairman. But the
fact is that it's up for should be up
for discussion from the public with
respect to the council and the chairman.
Um,
we're looking at transparency. We need
to have all the information. And I
respect Jennifer on what she's saying,
but
if we do some of the same things we've
done with the last council meeting when
we're not allowed to talk about the
whatever else we've been instructed to
talk about, we need to have all this
information up front. And I respect
Jennifer. I respect this council.
But as Mr. labor said it's a lot of
issues here and in order for these
issues to be addressed they need to be
for public and I'm going to remind
myself I was at a commissioner's meeting
and I know that you guys work hand in
hand we had an incident where the public
didn't have all the information period
it was postponed so I respectfully if
not I guess I'll have to address it
before the next council Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Okay.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead and unmute
yourself.
>> You hear me?
>> Yep. Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
>> Uh, madame chair, members of the
committee, Charles Miller, I'm speaking
to the substitute amendment for item 18.
This substitute perfectly encapsulates
the systemic problem with this entire
annexation process. Staff is asking you
to amend this ordinance today because
they failed to use accurate property
records and submitted a flawed legal
description. If the administration's
basic due diligence is so lacking that
they cannot even identify the correct
property owners on a 12,000 or 1250 acre
annexation. How can this committee
possibly trust their asurances regarding
public safety, closed loop water usage,
or the infrastructural impacts of the
data center this annexation is designed
for? You're rushing to annex 1,200 acres
of agricultural land to facilitate a
massive industrial development. Yet, the
paperwork is so sloppy, it requires a
mid-hering substitute just to get the
names right. Furthermore, this
substitute does nothing to address the
core failures of this application. There
is still no environmental impact study.
There is still no road maintenance
agreement and you are still relying on a
comprehensive plan your that your own
staff just admitted is 10 years out of
date. This substitute proves that this
process is rushed, flawed, and
administratively unsound. You should
reject this substitute and halt the
entire annexation until the
administration can produce a legally
accurate, fully audited and transparent
application. Thank you.
>> Okay, any other public comments?
Okay.
Can I get a motion and a second on the
substitution?
>> You have one.
>> Oh, sorry.
>> It's been long.
>> It has been long. Okay.
>> Madam Chair,
>> yes.
>> I'd like to
I do want to say first of all at the
public hearing, I know the mayor had
brought it up that some of the names
were incorrect last week and that there
were the changes need to be made. Um I
guess in defense of our staff, Mr. White
and through you, Madam Chairwoman, um
you'd used the current names that were
on the county maps. Is that correct,
>> Madam Chair? That is correct. So using
>> and how did we find out that those names
were incorrect?
>> U Madam Chair, through you uh received
an email um from the parties that found
out that their names were on the
documents.
>> Okay. Um
>> and asking for a correction.
>> Correct. And once I had that and we were
also given the deed of the actual
transaction because we don't have that
either or didn't have that at the time,
I made all those corrections as quickly
as I could and got that to the
attorney's office so that everything
could be updated right away. Okay. So,
you're just All right. I just want
everybody to understand how we how the
error was made and how we found out we
were in error and now we're doing our
best to correct at least this portion of
it. Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Okay. Any other discussion?
>> Chairwoman Emmens, I'm wondering if we
might be able to We've been at this now
for three hours almost. uh if we might
be able to take a break and have some
copies made um of the proposed
substitute for the people in the
audience who um are interested in having
that copy.
>> Jennifer, Jennifer, go ahead.
>> Um I can try and madam chair through
you. I can try to do that. My copier
actually went down just when I was
coming into this meeting. So I can
certainly go try to uh make those
copies. Um,
>> could we send them will can we just send
them digitally to or put them?
>> They will be posted later this
afternoon. So, as soon as we're done
with this meeting, I will make sure that
I go back and I do the posting. This is
our practice. We just don't post
anything until you guys have acted on
it. So, I'm I'm happy to do that. I'm
happy to try to go make some copies. I
just I don't know if I'm going to be
able to.
>> This is only second reading. So,
and I do think that's an important part
point. This is second reading for this.
This is not done today regardless of
what we do. So
>> to the extent that they No, it's
>> okay.
>> We've ended our public comment period.
I'm sorry.
Okay.
Any other discussion?
Okay. All those in favor of the um
substitution, please signify by saying I
>> I
>> opposed.
Okay. So the um substitution
passes. So now we go back to the
reconsideration.
>> Back to the main motion.
Okay. So no more discussion, right?
We're all good. Okay.
every everyone that's in favor of the
main motion. No.
>> I.
>> All those opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay. So, there will be no
recommendation from the public service
committee committee on this item at the
next meeting of the governing body.
And now we would like to take a break.
A five minute break.
I'm playing.
So
Sam
has said
>> over 200
because
>> so
obviously
All of the
That's
not
Baby,
baby.
So the
I'm going to go home and tell
Okay, we're going to go ahead and
reconvene.
Okay.
Do do you need
Okay. Okay.
Next item.
19.
Number 19, ordinance, second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of AG,
Agricultural MP public for an annex to
the city of Cheyenne, located west of
Roundtop Road and adjacent to HappyJack
Road. And I will remind the committee
that we just voted no on 18. So, we'll
probably or we probably want to do the
same on 19 since we didn't pass anything
to actually be zoned.
>> Madame Chairwoman, just to be clear, we
do have a substitute on this item, too.
So, just to be
>> Thank you.
>> staff report.
>> Madame Chair, members of the committee,
Counter Way, Planning and Development
Department. I was actually going to make
note of that as well with my staff
report. Um, I'll try to be brief because
of the direction the vote went on the
last one. Um, but just in case Monday
night is different than the committee
and it does go forward, I probably
should explain a little bit what the
assigned assigned zoning does. With any
annexation of land into the city limits,
we do assign it a city zone as basically
the base zone for that property. Uh,
that way it doesn't go unzoned. So, if
an annexation was to move forward with
approval, it does need the assigned
zoning to continue with it. Basically
with the assigned zoning staff
recommends that the larger parcel be
zoned AG agricultural and then that the
city's uh parcels would be zone P public
again because the recommendation of the
committee is not to approve the
annexation. I would say that with this
um ordinance as well uh it should
probably have no recommendation going
into next Monday. There is a substitute
though on this one uh just so I can add
that in here this time in instead of
doing what we did last time. Uh with the
substitute again it's just making name
changes. That's it. It's just correcting
names. Um that's all that substitute is.
It doesn't change anything else with the
ordinance or the report or anything like
that.
Uh with that I am available for any
questions.
questions for Connor.
Okay, seeing none,
um are is there any public comment
in the room or online? Okay, seeing
none,
uh can I get a motion and a second?
>> Motion to
approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay, Dr. Renie moved to approve and um
councelor Lebornne seconded.
>> Chairwoman, I move to amend by
substitute dated April 15th.
>> Second. Okay. Dr. Renie moved and Dr.
Aldrich seconded the uh substitution.
>> Is that correct, Connor? April 15th.
>> Okay.
Do I have to go public?
>> Okay. Is there any public comment on
that on the uh substitution?
>> Okay.
Okay. Does not look like we have any
public comment.
Um any comment or any discussion from
the committee?
Madame Chairman, just just for clarity,
um I I'm
seconded that motion and I'll be uh
voting in favor of this so that we have
a clear public record that's is correct
in all details. uh but I'm doing that in
the interest of discussion not
necessarily a belief that this is uh
I think I'll be explaining my position
here in just a moment.
>> Okay.
>> By voting no.
>> Okay. All those in support of the
substitution please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. So, the amendment passes.
We're back on the main uh motion.
Any discussion?
Okay. All those in favor,
all those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed.
>> So, the amendment or the um motion
fails. There'll be no recommendation
from the public service committee on
this item at the next governing body.
Next item
number 20, ordinance, second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located west of
Roundtop Road and adjacent to HappyJack
Road from AG Agricultural to BP Business
Park.
>> Is our staff report? Madam Chair,
committee again, Conor White, Planning
and Development Department. I'll try to
keep this one brief as well. I have a
feeling I know what the vote's going to
be. Um, but I do need to do the
explanation so that when we get to
Monday night, should the vote be
different and these items do move
forward, at least there has been some
sort of discussion on them.
So, the zone change application is
proposed um proposes changing the zoning
from AG agricultural to BP business park
for roughly 1,197.76
acres of land. Uh that is just the Cox
Ranch land. So, this does not the zone
change has nothing to do with the
city-owned parcels.
The land is currently vacant. Uh the
applicant has requested a change to the
future land use map to change the
designation from urban transition
residential to uh slashno designation to
mixeduse employment. The future land use
map um as was stated by Seth earlier
basically the future land use map
amendment would not come before this uh
basically before council uh until next
Monday. It gets introduced and then
would have discussion afterwards. So
depending how next Monday goes, future
land use map uh may not really matter.
But that was submitted um because it's a
resolution to time it with everything
else. It does have the delayed submitt,
but they did request a future land use
map amendment uh to mixeduse employment.
I should note uh with future land use
map amendments, they do go to county
commissioners for comment. Comment only.
There is no vote or anything by county
commissioners. So this future land use
map did go to county commissioners. They
made absolutely no comment.
The current uh future land use
designation uh does the current future
land use designation of urban transition
residential does not support the zone
change to business park. Should the
future land use designation be approved,
it would support the BP zone uh as that
designation would anticipate more
commercial and industrial type uh zone
districts.
The BP district is applicable to areas
on the edge of the community uh that are
intended to support large-scale
industrial, manufacturing, shipping,
research and development and data center
uses. The BP zone is a mix of our LI,
HI, CB zones, uh which allows for many
different industrial and commercial
uses. The BP zone will allow this
property to develop with more uses uh
than what is allowed in the AG zone.
Proposed zoning could be part of the
extension of North Range Business Park
or it could be its own uh business park
as it is over the 320 acres required for
the BP zone. And this property is on the
edge of the community.
Planning Commission did recommend
approval. Staff recommended approval.
I'm available for questions.
>> Okay. Any questions for staff?
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> is there any substitute on this?
>> I didn't see one, but I just wanted to
make sure.
>> Madam Chair, through you. No, there is
no substitute on this. Uh the ordinance
doesn't actually define it doesn't
basically have the names of the
ownership in there. Zoning is more tied
to the land itself with the legal
description than it is. Actually, most
ordinances are tied to the legal
description with the land, but there are
no names mentioned in the ordinance, so
no substitute.
>> Um, Councilman Labour, do you have a
question?
>> No.
>> Okay.
Okay.
Um, is there any public comment on
number on this item?
>> Madam Chair, woman, Dr. Evans, Brad
Evans, AVI, agent for the owner and
applicant. Just wanted to let you know
we're we still believe if if the city
were to annex this property that BP
would be a a zoning that would be would
fit and be happy to answer any questions
uh the committee had on that.
>> Thank you. Any questions for Mr. Emmens?
Okay.
>> Oh. Um okay, Mr. Miller?
Oh, maybe not.
>> I think I hit it.
>> Mr. Miller, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yep.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Charles Miller, I'm speaking to item 20.
First, let the official record reflect
that during the previous agenda item,
the clerk explicitly stated aloud that
my hand was raised for public comment.
Madam Chair, you actively ignored it,
stating there was no public comment and
closed the floor, denying a citizen.
>> Wait, wait, wait. Mr. Miller, your hand
went down. So, that was not done on
purpose. It was just that it show it
showed that you had lowered your hand.
So, go ahead.
>> Um, well, I'm just going to go ahead and
continue. Maybe it was a technical
glitch. I I believe there's probably
some uh ways to determine that in the
logs of the software, but uh but denying
a citizen the right to speak after they
have been visibly and audibly
acknowledged in a limited public forum
is a flagrant violation of the
procedural due process and the Wyoming
Public Meetings Act. That suppression of
speech is now a permanent part of this
hearing's transcript. Regarding item 20
itself, the business park resoning is
procedurally invalid. Not only has this
committee rightly signaled its intent to
reject the underlying annexation, but
your own staff just admitted on the
record that the future land use map
amendment required to support this
zoning has not yet been adopted. You
cannot legally reszone 1200 acres to an
industrial use when the controlling
master plan does not yet permit it. I
urge you to formally vote no on this
item to definitively kill this
outofsequence land grab. And I strongly
suggest this committee cease its
attempts to silence the public before
you completely invalidate today's
proceedings. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Miller. Anyone else?
>> Your hand is raised again. Did you have
something else you wanted to say?
>> Talking to you.
>> Yeah.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> No. No.
>> Okay. Lower your hand, please.
>> Go ahead.
>> Good afternoon, Madam Chair, members of
the public service committee. Um, if you
show up in person, uh, usually your
opportunity to speak won't get squalled.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Okay.
Any other public comment?
Okay. So, we have a second. We have a
motion. We have second. We're ready to
vote, right?
>> We did.
Okay.
>> Do we have a motion and a second?
>> Move to
I don't even remember. Approve. It's an
ordinance.
>> Okay. We have a motion to
approve
by Dr. Renie. Is there a second?
Okay, that uh motion fails for lack of a
second.
Number Okay.
>> Number 24. Resolution authorizing the
mayor and the city clerk to sign a final
plat for Bison Apartment, City of
Cheyenne, Larry County, Wyoming, north
of West College Drive, east of Grand
Harmony Boulevard, and west of Waltershy
Boulevard.
Oh, sorry. Staff report.
Yeah.
Go ahead, Martin.
>> All right, Madame Chair, members of the
committee, Morgan Dennis, Planning and
Development. Um, this is an expedited
plat for 1.88 88 acres located
north of West College Drive, west of
Waltershide Boulevard and east of Grand
Harmony Boulevard. The site is currently
finishing construction of eight forplex
buildings. Um the purpose of this plat
is to create individual lots for the
building. Um there is a common lot that
is on this plat. Um the responsibility
of maintenance for that common lot will
be split amongst the owners of all the
buildings. So that's an eighth interest
for each building owner and each of
those building owners will be
responsible with maintaining the current
approved site plan. The future land use
map designates this area as mixeduse
commercial. The zoning for this parcel
is CB. Multi-dwelling buildings are
conditional use in the CB zone. This
parcel received uh approval for a
multi-dwelling building from the board
of adjustments in November of 2024. Uh
in the CB zone there are no minimum no
lot minimums for frontage or area so all
lots proposed are buildable. Uh planning
commission heard this on April 6th and
recommends approval. I stand for
questions.
>> Are there questions for Morgan?
Councilman Leborn.
>> Excuse me. Um Madam Chair, um did you
say that these were forplexes?
>> Uh yes, Madam Chair through you. Yes.
Um,
a lot of forplexes have a different
second floor than the first floor.
>> So, is that the case here where
>> um the applicant is here to speak to
that if
>> going to get an answer
>> that answer. Is there any other
questions for Morgan while we have her
up here? Okay,
good. We have the developer
speak, please.
Madam Chair, through you John Sers's
agent for trigger. So let me address
Pete's question. These are forplexes,
but it's an individual owner for the
entire building, not per unit. We're not
doing condos on it. So based on the
marketing situation for financing, it's
easier for them to have the entire
building than to do a condo map and all
that. So each building will be its own
separate individual owner. They will
have the 1/8 interest tied to the common
open space which will take care of
landscaping, parking lot and trash and
so forth. So that is how we were working
that through the city further request
and making sure that we had that noted
on the plat and that it complies with
the approved site plan and they must
still conform with the site plan after
this plat goes through. As uh Morgan did
a great job. We uh went ahead and did
the news taking the necessary steps. We
went ahead and got the site plan
approved. We've gone ahead. We do have a
buyer, but their interest is is to break
each individual building off for
subsequent family members. So, that is
the reason we bring forward the plat
especially on the forplexes and stand
for any questions.
>> Thank you. Oh, wait. Dr. Renie.
>> So, looking at the map, we Sorry, Madam
Chairwoman. Through you to Mr. Sers. Um
we have the eight units all divided but
then the parking lot is common area is
that
>> madam chair through you to m Dr. Randy
so on that particular piece it is only
just the surrounding for the building
itself and the staircase everything else
including the green space and the
multiple easements as you see to the
south of there that we really can't
build anything in is all green space and
and decorated and done at this point. We
are finishing up the inside of the
buildings. But yes, there is only eight
buildings and everything else that is
not tied directly to the building is all
common space open space 1/8 interest by
all parties.
>> Okay. Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Thank you, Mr. Sers.
Okay. Is there any public comment either
in person or online on this item?
Okay. Seeing none, can I get a motion
and a second?
>> I would so move to approve.
>> Adopt.
>> Dr. Ren, Dr. Aldridge move to adopt. And
um Councilman Leborn seconded.
Is there any discussion?
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
So the recommendation from the public
service committee will be to approve at
the next meeting of the governing body.
Next item
>> number 25 resolution authorizing the
mayor and the city clerk to sign a final
plot for O'Neal Edge City of Cheyenne
Larmy County Wyoming located southwest
of the intersection of West Fifth Street
and O'Neal Avenue.
>> Staff report please. Madame Chair,
members of the committee, Morgan Dennis,
Planning and Development. This is
another expedited plat but for 0.3 acres
located southwest of the intersection of
West Fifth and O'Neal Avenue. This lot
is currently vacant and the propo the
proposal for this plot is to create five
lots for residential development. The
future land use map designates this area
as urban residential. Zoning for the
parcel is MR medium density residential.
Surrounding development in the in the
area is primarily residential. Four of
the proposed lots will fall within the
SD3 lot type and the remaining lot will
be considered DD7.
All lots are all lots proposed are
buildable in the MR zone. On the
preliminary map, there is not a water or
sewer service easement. This easement
has been requested by the board of
public utilities prior to signing. Uh
this easement will need to be added to
the final plat. Um and the plat before
you does have this easement running
along along it. Uh planning commission
heard this on April 6 and recommends
approval with the condition that the
water and sewer easement is added prior
to signing. And I stand for questions.
>> Any questions for Morgan? Dr. Renie,
>> pardon me.
>> Oh, okay.
Okay. Is there a developer?
>> Madam Chair, members of the public
service committee, this is officially
the longest public service committee
I've been in for sure. Um, yeah,
glad we could share it together. Brandon
Swain, I'm in W three. Uh, this project
is a simply uh, excuse me, essentially a
duplicate of a project uh that I've
recently completed construction on. I
believe the final plat was approved um
before most of these members of the
governing body sometime uh end of 2024
possibly. Uh what it's going to result
in is one duplex unit uh on that
remainder lot fronting Fifth Street. Uh
duplex meaning two units on one common
lot. The other four units facing O'Neal
uh will be twin homes. I just completed
the project at Fifth Street and Snyder
did hold that price point to 250,000.
it's nearly impossible to do, but these
infill lots, these tighter lots with no
minimum lot size requirements do help
aid that possibility. So, I'm very
grateful for that. Um, that being said,
I I stand for any questions.
>> Okay. Any questions for Mr. Swain?
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Chairwoman Emmens. Brandon, are
these similar to what you did over by
Kerry?
>> Uh, so the Kerry cottages are going to
be two stories, 1,200 ft², three bed,
three bath, onecar garage. Um, these
units are two beded, two bath, around
740 square feet. Um, and they're they're
just a singlestory product. Um, if
you're in that Snyder Fifth Street area,
they're right there on the southeast
corner. So, I'd encourage you to take a
look. I'll even send you a lockbox code
if you'd like to walk inside.
>> So, one level on a concrete slab or
>> correct. Okay. Thank you.
>> Yep. One level on a concrete slab. And
and actually that that does remind me um
at planning commission. I I probably
should have mentioned it. I'll mention
it now. This plat will accompany
accompany, excuse me, two relief
processes. Um, one is going to be for a
reduced front setback for the Fifth
Street Towns project, which is at Fifth
and Snider. I had to ask for both relief
in the front and rear. Um, this lot is
more generous in area, so we're only
looking at a reduced front setback. Uh,
the rear setback will hold the lot line
at 20 ft. Um, and then, uh, these do not
have garages. Uh, this UDC requires two
parking spots per unit, which I do have
if you factor in the O'Neal frontage and
Fifth Street frontage. However, the UDC
specifies that that parking allocation
has to be the frontage per lot. So, in
addition to this plot that you see
before you, administratively, there'll
be um a submission for reduced front
setback and then reduced parking
requirements to bring that from two
spaces to one. Practically speaking, I
believe I meet the requirement, but it's
not always a matter of pragmatics. It's
also juggling conforming with the UDC.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other public comment?
>> Okay. Hearing none. Seeing none.
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a motion from Dr. Renie
and a second from Dr. Aldridge.
>> Madam Chairwoman, can I just be sure
that we include the condition in the
motion? I'm sorry.
>> No. With condition A, the requirement
for the easement
Okay,
>> thank you for catching that.
>> Second that addition
>> is a friendly amendment.
>> Okay,
any other discussion? Okay, all those in
favor please signify by saying I
>> I
>> and opposed.
Uh there will I'm sorry the
recommendation from the public service
committee will be to adopt at the next
governing B body
>> number 27 resolution overruling the
planning commission's disapproval of an
amendment to the future land use map of
plan Cheyenne changing the land use
designation from mixeduse residential to
mixeduse employment for property
generally located south of I80 east of
east of Southwest Five
>> staff report.
>> Madam chair, members of the committee,
um 5 years ago when this meeting
started, I talked about an item
that was um regarding a zone change for
land located near Southwest Drive and I
80 and the BNSF railroad. Um this
property in order to be zoned uh LI and
conform with the future land use map
would need a future landings map
amendment. Um that future land use map
amendment is actually the next item on
the agenda. At the planning commission
there was a vote on the future land use
map amendment and the planning
commission voted 32
in favor of the amendment. However, the
planning commission bylaws state that a
chair only votes in case in the case of
a tie and state statute says you only
adopt plans if you have a majority of
the commission voting yes. So, we have a
weird situation here where the chair
would need to vote to make it a 42 vote
or a three-3 vote, one way or the other.
Um, but was unable to vote because it
wasn't a tie vote per the planning
commission bylaw. So, um, I don't even
know if I should tell you if the
planning commission approved it or
denied it. Officially, I guess it's
denied. um
>> fun fun times. But that's the reason we
have this item in front of you is
because if you want to approve the
future land use map uh amendment um the
state statute says you need to overrule
the planning commission's decision on a
plan. And so this is a plan. Planning
commission approves and and and
officially approves those plans. And so
now the governing body has to overrule
that. However, um due to the fact that
overruling this is probably contingent
on whether or not you like what the
proposal is, I will go over that actual
proposal. Um so you know what you're go
voting on which is the actual proposal
is the next item on the agenda. Um
have to hit the share screen here.
>> Madam Chairwoman,
>> yes.
>> I have a question for Mr. Lloyd. If we
were not to if we voted to not overrule
planning commission then do we even look
at the next item on the agenda?
>> Uh it's on your agenda madam chair
through it's on your agenda. So I'd
assume you'd have to vote that one down
as well. Um I would highly recommend you
use the same vote on this one as on the
next item whichever your choice is.
>> Yes.
>> And that's why I'm going to go over the
next item on the agenda and I probably
will not present on the next item unless
you really want me to.
>> Thank you, Madam Chair. Um, the future
land use map of the area shows a future
land use designations of mixeduse
residential and mixed use commercial
west of the BNSF railroad tracks and
open space and parks um and a little bit
of public as well, but by and large it
does not have industrial or mixeduse
employment on this side of the on this
this side of the tracks. Um, we also
have some residential development to the
south, further to the south, and then
also immediately to the southwest of
this property. So, those are arguments
against changing the future land use map
of this location because we don't have
any mixed use employment on this side of
the railroad tracks and everything else
around it is designated for eventual
residential development and it may have
negatively affect the existing property
owners to the south and southwest.
However, when we look at zoning and
actual development, we have LII zoning
on three sides. Right now, we have kind
of more industrial development on the
east across the railroad tracks and also
to the north. Um, specifically to
northwest, it's more industrial style
style development. So, it comes down to
uh it's really a balancing act here. Um,
you can tell from the staff report
there's very good reasons to approve
this. There's also very good reasons to
deny this. The planning commission was
obviously pretty divided on this as
well. Um, so at the end of the day, it's
probably kind of up to you guys. We
don't really have a great
recommendation. Staff kind of ended up
leaning on the side of denial. Um, based
on the future land use plan for the
entire area and how that this this
future future land use map amendment
would kind of um bring mixed use
employment across tracks where it hasn't
been previously. But the uh um there's
obviously definitely good reasons to
approve this application as well. So uh
I'm available for any questions on this.
Um hopefully you guys still are able to
consider this item um after a long
meeting.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> Madam Chairwoman, um through Mr. Lloyd,
can
help me um refresh my memory with the
mixeduse employment. What does
How does that differ from the LI? I
mean, we discussed this earlier
>> and it was surrounded by light
industrial.
>> So, so what are we in interjecting into
this that's different?
>> Okay. So, Miss Madam Chair, I'll I'll
step back a moment. We've got two
different levels um that we work with in
when it comes to land use. One is the
plan level. This is what we think will
happen in the future for the area. The
other is the zoning level. This is where
we actually regulate things. Um, so
zoning and the long range plan don't
always mesh completely together. Um,
sometimes we want areas to change in the
future. Sometimes we think, "Oh, this
area would be a great place for
residential, or this would be a great
place for industrial, even though it's a
field now, or there's some homes here,
but they're not exactly um, you know,
the neighborhood is is kind of
transforming into industrial area. So
maybe we approp it' be appropriate to be
industrial, or maybe vice versa, as it
transforming into residential area, and
it should be residential." On our future
land use plan, we don't have an LI
designation. So, let me get that out
there. Right now, there is no LI on the
future land use plan. The future land
use plan would suggest the LI zoning
occurs in the mixeduse employment
designation or the industrial
designation. Um, on the map on the
screen, you can see some purple area to
the northeast kind of kitty corner of
the subject property. That's what the
industrial designation looks like. That
designation would also allow for hi or
heavy industrial zoning.
The lighter purple color is mixeduse
employment designation. That would allow
for a mix of commercial zoning like a CB
zone or a light industrial zoning like
the LI zone or the mixeduse employment
zone which to be frank the city hasn't
used very often. I think we have one
parcel zone to mixed use employment in
the entire city. Also a more recent
update would be the BP zone if the
region was large enough. Mixed use
employment would support the BP zone.
So the mixed use employment future land
use category has a few different zones
that would be appropriate. One of which
would include the LI zone. The zoning
map has the LI zone and this proposal
that's in front of you would extend
mixeduse employment across the railroad
tracks which would then support LI
zoning in this area. Um right now
despite the LI zoning around the future
land use plan is telling us that we want
this area to become residential and
commercial. we want the industrial uses
to leave essentially. Um, but by
extending mixed use employment over
here, we're saying industrial is okay in
this area. We're okay with this area
retaining that industrial character. So
that's that's the question in front of
you is in the long range scheme of
things, is this area around I80,
Southwest Drive and the BNSF railroad
track an area that we want to continue
as industrial or is it an area that we
want to see um transform into a
residential, maybe a little bit of
commercial development? Right now, the
future land use plan is saying that we
want it to transform. If you make this
amendment, we're saying we're okay with
it not transforming. We're okay with it
retaining kind of an industrial
character in this area.
Hope that answers your question,
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Do I need more?
>> That yes, that did answer my question up
to a point. As I said, we discussed this
earlier and it seemed like it was
surrounded by light industrial. So
changing um
the zone or seemed to at least multiuse
employment seems to be appropriate. I
guess what I threw me off was that I
thought at the start of the discussion
or that explanation Mr. Lloyd said that
really the staff's recommendation was to
leave it unchanged or
>> madam chair through you the staff's
recommendation is to leave it unchanged.
Um, but that's I mean we're talking
about a nearly 50/50. Staff went back
and forth on this, but ultimately our
recommendation is leave it unchanged.
>> So the staff, Madam Chairwoman, so the
slight majority sentiment of the staff
is that it still has potential for res
residential and mixeduse residential
development.
>> Madam Chair, that's fair. um looking at
how much development we're having in the
region, large acre parcels possibly
becoming more data center-l like the
community needs places to have
residential. There's already residential
in the area. Um so it'd be uh
probably more compatible with the
existing residents to have residential
here. However, the existing residential
areas are in the county. They're lu
zoned. They have the potential to get a
conditional use to put something
industrial on those parcels. So, it is,
as I said, there's there's good reasons
both ways on the balance. Staff
recommends um keeping it as mixeduse
residential. Um but it certainly has
some robust arguments to move it along
to a mixed use employment and allow the
white industrial zoning.
>> So, Madam Chairman, my last question is
first of all, I want to congratulate
you, Seth, because in all my 27 plus
years, I don't ever remember having to
overrule the planning commission. So
there's always something new coming
along. Good job. Um and then
so um
but
but so if we think we should sustain the
mixeduse residential
then we vote against overrule. We vote
against overruling.
>> Madam chair that is correct. If you want
for this area
>> vote no on the next two items. Just
wanted to make sure that it's kind we're
kind of doing a double negative and I
wanted to make sure I had it
>> correct
>> straight. All right. Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge. Chairwoman Emmens. Um I
can see why your committee and by the
planning commission is torn on this. Um
I mean we have the animal shelter on the
west side of Southwest. I've noticed
lately just within the last six months
or so there's a huge storage facility
now on the west side of Southwest Drive.
We have Ryman Construction over in that
LI area to the east. And then we also
have the APF Wyatt. We have Department
of Corrections, all of those that are
south of um I 80. And then we have the
heavy industrial with Puma Steel north
of I80. Uh Gil Windows and all of those
out there. Um I'm going to be a no vote
today. Um because
I want to make sure this is right. I
want I actually believe this is a better
light industrial area because of where
it's at. So I should be a
>> yes.
>> A yes vote. Okay.
>> Lord.
Okay. So yikes. Um because I think most
of those residences there have been I
mean I think a lot of people are going
into that light industrial arena and a
lot of the residential areas are being
sold out. Um I'm guessing that some of
them were two and five acre lots
originally at some point. Um, but I know
there was a it became very contentious
when there was talk about building
residential in this area um, a couple of
years ago. So, um, and I I'm just not a
big fan of putting residential right
there along the interstate and along all
of those other industrial areas that I
don't see it moving anytime soon. So,
for that reason, I'll be a yes vote,
which really is a no vote. Whatever.
Once again, just for the record, Madam
Chair, if you I may, a yes vote supports
light industrial zoning. A no vote
supports uh uh more of a residential uh
plan for this area.
>> Super glad I'm not the
Okay. Um
any public comment,
Mr. Sers?
Madam Chair, through you John Sers's
agent for True Grit. Dr. Aldridge, you
were gonna have to do CPR there for a
second just just as you started that
before I even got to speak. I was a
little nervous there, but good. So, back
to this. We are surrounded by the LI.
We've asked for the LI. You previously
approved earlier today or this morning,
I guess, uh, on that matter.
Dr. any I've been doing this a long time
with you and I've never been here this
long, especially for this meeting. Um,
with that said, there was a situation
that occurred during the the planning
commission that I must point out. Um,
because there was only six members
present. Mr. Wigum, the chair, is not
allowed to vote unless there is a tie.
Um, three votes yes, two votes no. You
didn't have your seventh person there to
either make a yes or a no. That doesn't
allow Mr. Wigum to make a decision
unless it had been a tie. After we all
scrambled for a bit, Boyd said off the
record he would have approved, but he
didn't have the capabilities of saying a
yes vote at that point. So that left our
hands tied, hence the reason we're here
doing something we haven't done as an
Yeah, there we go. Um, so with that in
mind, I would appreciate if you would
consider the idea that the area is LI,
that we are still holding true with the
idea of combining all three parcels to
the LI, moving forward with the
different options that we have for the
LI zoning as we are getting the phone
calls for different ideas in this area.
And I'd stand for any questions.
>> Any questions for Mr. Ser. Okay. Any
other public comment? I saw Mr. Miller's
hand raised.
I think that's
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yep. Uh,
>> madam chair, members of the committee,
my name is Charles Miller. I'll keep
this brief as I have no desire to add
another five years to Mr. Lloyd's
timeline. Speaking to items 27 and 28.
Staff just admitted on the record that
the planning commission vote was a legal
disapproval because it failed to secure
the majority required by Wyoming State
Statutes 151505.
Mr. Lloyd called this a weird situation,
but there is nothing weird about the
law. The law requires four votes for
approval. The developer got three. In
any other context, that is a final
decision. What we are witnessing today
is administrative bias in its purest
form. Earlier in this meeting, we
established a record of this committee
attempting to chill public speech to
protect the developers narrative. Now,
we see the administration asking you to
bypass a lawful statutory roadblock and
ignore the staff's own recommendation
for residential use simply because the
legal outcome was inconvenient for a
commercial interest. This body routinely
holds private Laramie County residents
to the absolute letter of the municipal
code for the smallest infractions. Yet,
here you are being asked to deploy an
executive override to bypass your own
citizen board's disapproval.
If you vote to advance this override
today, you are cementing a formal record
of arbitrary and arbitrary and selective
municipal enforcement. You are
generating the exact documentation
required for a 14th amendment equal
protection claim. You cannot enforce the
law strictly when it applies to citizens
and then bypass the law entirely to
facilitate industrial expansion for
developers. I urge this committee to
respect the statutory process, respect
the legal outcome of the planning
commission's vote, and reject this
override. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Think about
it. I
um for Mr. Lloyd is the difference
the fact that the future land use map is
involved because in the past
when there's been
a recommendation from the planning
commission we've been told just that
that it is a recommendation and we do
not have to I mean we can if we wish we
can vote differently so why
so essentially because it failed in
planning commission. We have a no
recommendation from them. So why are we
having to overrule this?
>> Mr. Chair, uh sorry, Madam Chair,
through you too, Dr. Renie. Um the
planning commission require per state
statute, planning commission requires
four yes votes to approve an item. Um it
has to have a majority of the
commission, not a majority of those
present in voting or the majority of the
quorum or whatever it is. Um as such the
um per Wyoming state statute this has
failed at the planning commission. Also
per Wyoming state statute the city
council has every right to overrule the
planning commission and that's the
process we're doing right now. In the
past some items are just recommendations
from the planning commission. So like on
his own change the planning commission
just recommends and then you take that
recommendation to consideration make
your own vote. It doesn't matter if
you're overruling them or not overruling
them or agreeing with them. whatever it
is, you make your own vote and the plan
commission just recommends. It's a
little bit different when it comes to
master plans or long-range plans or
comprehensive.
>> That's why I want to know what the
difference was because there's so many
times we've been an applicant will not
get the recommendation they wanted in
planning commission and decided to go
through city council anyway. And again,
we were told at that point, well, it's a
recommendation. You can take it or leave
it. So, I want to know why that why this
one was different. So, all right. Thank
you, Madam Chair, Chairwoman, and I Yes.
>> Okay. Uh, any other public comment?
>> Okay. Can I get a motion and a second?
>> I would move to approve.
>> Okay. I have a motion to approve.
>> Second. It's a because it's a
resolution.
>> Sorry. Whatever.
>> And a second from Dr. Renie.
Um, discussion.
Madame Chairman, I think I'm going to
support the resolution. I mean, early on
I although I understand um
the department's maybe slight preference
that this should stay residential, it
when I look at that area, it's pretty
much becoming at least light industrial.
So, um and the fact that it's surrounded
by light to heavy industrial, it seems
to me that will be the direction that's
going to go. So,
um, so I voted in favor of that earlier.
So, I guess in order to be consistent, I
will vote in favor of adopting the
resolution.
>> Okay. Dr. Aldridge.
>> Oh, I'm just waiting to vote.
>> Okay. Um, all those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And opposed.
>> Okay. The recommendation from the public
service committee will be to adopt at
the next meeting of the governing body.
>> Number 20. Resolution amending the
future land use map of plan Cheyenne,
changing the land use designation from
mixeduse residential to mixeduse
employment for property generally
located south of I80 and east of
Southwest Drive.
>> There's staff report.
>> Go ahead, Seth. M
>> madam chair, this is Seth with the
planning development department. I
pretty much already gave the report on
this item with the last item just for
clarity as to what you were voting on
with the last item. So I have no further
comments unless you have questions for
me. Okay. Are there questions for staff?
All right. Um, is there any public
comment?
Okay. Hearing none.
>> She would move to adopt.
>> Dr. um Aldridge moved to adopt. Dr.
Renie seconded. Any discussion from the
committee?
>> Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I. I
>> and those opposed.
Um the recommendation from the public
service committee will be to adopt at
the next meeting of the governing body.
>> Number 29 resolution authorizing the
mayor and the city clerk to sign a final
plat for dry Dry Creek Vista City of
Cheyenne, Larie County, Wyoming, east of
North College Drive and north of Rock
Spring Street. Staff report.
>> Chair, members of committee, Connor
White, Planning Development Department.
I decided to switch where I was sitting.
I'm gonna stand at the podium this time.
The plat before you, um, you'll probably
recognize it, uh, because we did have
one, the preliminary plat that came
through council, as well as we just had
the vacation that was approved, uh, for
the right ofway that is part of this
plat.
Um, so this is the final plat for uh,
Dry Creek Vista. Uh, this takes into
account the vacated right ofway for
Frank Court. It turns it into from
basically two lots into three lots.
The existing residential houses will
each be on their own existing lot and
then that larger lot uh lot three will
just be a vacant lot for future uh
residential development.
There are easements provided. And I know
there was some discussion on how will
certain homes be able to access their
property. Lot one does have an access
easement along the basically the east or
sorry west side of lot two that provides
access all the way back. Um
this plat was heard by planning
commission was recommended for approval.
Uh staff does recommend approval as
well. There is a condition uh that staff
has for this plat. is just that we have
uh some sort of documentation of the
ownership for East West vacated Frank
Court. There's been a lot of
this property has been very interesting
and we're glad to finally see it
platted, but we're hoping that we can
just get all the ownership stuff figured
out because back in the day, the east
west portion of Frank was vacated by
back in the county.
Documentation wasn't really provided. Uh
no clue who the ownership was supposed
to go to. the vacation wasn't recorded.
The county recently did that I think
last summer, went back and redid the
resolution and there's still kind of the
question of ownership. So, we just want
to make sure we've got all the ownership
figured out, but that is basically a
requirement to have that prior to
signing of the plat. So, that's the only
condition staff would want to see
continued. Planning Commission did
recommend that condition as well. I'm
available for any questions.
Any questions for staff?
Okay.
Is there any public comment on this
item?
Seeing none,
>> move to adopt with the recommendation
with the
condition. Sorry.
>> Dr. Al Dr. Aldridge moved and Dr. Renie
seconded.
Um any discussion from the committee?
Hearing
none. All those in favor, please signify
by saying I. I.
>> Those opposed.
>> And with that, it concludes our meeting.